<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
  <front>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The bot that makes history</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-9261-8390</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Falk</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Michael Falk</string-name>
          <email>michael.falk@unimelb.edu.au</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-3500-9772</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ford</surname>
            <given-names>Heather</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Heather Ford</string-name>
          <email>heather.ford@uts.edu.au</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-8304-7108</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Pietsch</surname>
            <given-names>Tamson</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Tamson Pietsch</string-name>
          <email>tamson.pietsch@uts.edu.au</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-5796-4105</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Tkacz</surname>
            <given-names>Nathaniel</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Nathaniel Tkacz</string-name>
          <email>n.tkacz@gold.ac.uk</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3">c</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff-1">
        <institution-wrap>
          <institution>University of Melbourne</institution>
        </institution-wrap>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff-2">
        <institution-wrap>
          <institution>University of Technology, Sydney</institution>
        </institution-wrap>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff-3">
        <institution-wrap>
          <institution>Goldsmiths, University of London</institution>
        </institution-wrap>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor-1">michael.falk@unimelb.edu.au</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <history/>
      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
        <kwd>Wikipedia; bots; temporal regime; time; historicity; trace
ethnography</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="introduction-wikipedia-and-the-technicity-of-time">
      <title>Introduction: Wikipedia and The Technicity of Time</title>
      <p>Time is a supple medium. It winds itself into many shapes. It
  surges through the heartwood. It lies upon the bark. It carves rock
  and unfolds in song. It creates myriad structures, then entropically
  destroys them. It races, dallies, recurs, reverses, accelerates,
  splits and stops.</p>
      <p>Despite its suppleness, time has definite characteristics. It forms
  rhythms. It weaves people and plants and animals into lives and
  seasons. It founds eras.</p>
      <p>What are the characteristics of time in the digital era? The
  question has been a major preoccupation for humanists and social
  scientists in the twenty-first century. Theorists in many disciplines
  have argued that ‘presentism’ is the dominant ‘temporal regime’ of the
  twenty-first century
  (<xref alt="Assmann 2020" rid="ref-assmann_is_2020" ref-type="bibr">Assmann
  2020</xref>;
  <xref alt="Hartog 2017" rid="ref-hartog_regimes_2017" ref-type="bibr">Hartog
  2017</xref>). We inhabit a ‘broad present’
  (<xref alt="Gumbrecht 2014" rid="ref-gumbrecht_our_2014" ref-type="bibr">Gumbrecht
  2014</xref>) or a ‘timeless time’
  (<xref alt="Castells 2010" rid="ref-castells_rise_2010" ref-type="bibr">Castells
  2010</xref>) in which big data and frictionless communication have
  conspired with the cult of memory to abolish the future and bring the
  past into the present. We live in a rubble-world of accumulating fact.
  Other theorists have diagnosed the problem as ‘temporal acceleration’.
  We experience time as running ever faster, argues Wajcman
  (<xref alt="2015, 77" rid="ref-wajcman_pressed_2015" ref-type="bibr">2015,
  77</xref>), because it has become ‘deroutinized’. We are trapped in
  the present because we are present in so many places at once: on the
  phone to daycare while picking up dinner ingredients in the
  supermarket on our lunchbreak at work. Digital media are the
  handmaidens of post-industrial capitalism. Without them, we would be
  unable to maintain the modicum of order we currently enjoy.</p>
      <p>A weakness of many theories of temporality is their focus on the
  <italic>products</italic> rather than the <italic>production</italic>
  of temporal regimes. To characterise a temporal regime, the theorist
  considers some cultural products, such as literary texts
  (<xref alt="Gumbrecht 2014" rid="ref-gumbrecht_our_2014" ref-type="bibr">Gumbrecht
  2014</xref>;
  <xref alt="Hartog 2017" rid="ref-hartog_regimes_2017" ref-type="bibr">Hartog
  2017</xref>) or work-time statistics
  (<xref alt="Castells 2010" rid="ref-castells_rise_2010" ref-type="bibr">Castells
  2010</xref>) and tries to determine what kind of temporal regime those
  products represent. Such accounts necessarily raise the question: how
  is it possible to erect a temporal regime in the first place? A
  compelling answer is given by Orlikowski and Yates
  (<xref alt="2002" rid="ref-orlikowski_its_2002" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>),
  who argue that the temporal regime of an organisation is produced by
  the ‘practices’ of its members. Such practices can modify a temporal
  regime ‘implicitly’ or ‘explicitly’
  (<xref alt="2002, 687" rid="ref-orlikowski_its_2002" ref-type="bibr">2002,
  687</xref>), though in either case the key force of change is
  <italic>repetition</italic>, or ‘recurrent action’
  (<xref alt="2002, 696" rid="ref-orlikowski_its_2002" ref-type="bibr">2002,
  696</xref>). Temporal regimes are rhythmical. They are produced by the
  recurrent actions of people, who learn to act in concert as the
  members of an orchestra.</p>
      <p>In this paper, we build on Orlikowski and Yates’s theory of
  temporal structuration to describe the temporal regime of Wikipedia.
  We show that to explain Wikipedia’s temporal regime, it is necessary
  to supplement Orlikowski and Yates’s theory of
  <italic>repetition</italic> with a theory of time’s
  <italic>representation</italic> and its <italic>technicity</italic>.
  Only by accounting for these three aspects of time can we adequately
  answer our central questions: (1) what is Wikipedia time? and (2) what
  can it tell us about digital time more broadly?</p>
      <p>Our central case study is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Yapperbot">Yapperbot/uncurrenter</ext-link>,
  a ‘bot’ or computer program that polices the barrier between past and
  present on English Wikipedia. We situate Yapperbot/uncurrenter in
  Wikipedia’s broader sociotechnical systems. We examine how it
  interacts with human editors. We show how it fits into Wikipedia’s
  complex array of interfaces and data streams. We present
  Yapperbot/uncurrenter as a prime example of the ‘technicity of time’.
  It is a technology that attempts to make time concrete, to freeze it
  into an object. Yapperbot/uncurrenter is like the master’s clock in an
  eighteenth-century factory. It ticks regularly
  (<italic>repetition</italic>), shows the time
  (<italic>representation</italic>) and acts impersonally
  (<italic>technicity</italic>).</p>
      <p>Yapperbot/uncurrenter performs a single, simple task. Each hour, it
  scans English Wikipedia, finding every article that ‘transcludes’
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Current">Template:Current</ext-link>.
  If the article has not been edited in over five hours, it deletes the
  template.</p>
      <p>A ‘template’ is a microprogram that peforms a common task. In the
  case of Template:Current, the editor inserts the code
  <monospace>{current}</monospace> into an article. This adds a warning
  banner to the article (Figure ), and automatically adds the article to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Current_events">Category:Current_events</ext-link>.
  When Yapperbot/uncurrenter deletes the template, the banner
  disappears, as does the article’s categorisation as a ‘current event’.
  This would seem to consign the article to the past. But here lies the
  first twist in the tale. When Yapperbot/uncurrenter deletes
  Template:Current, it leaves an oddly contradictory message in the
  article’s edit history:</p>
      <disp-quote>
        <p>Auto-removing {{current}} - no edits in 5hrs+. The event may
    still be current, but
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Current">the
    {{current}} template is designed only for articles which many
    editors are editing, and is usually up for less than a
    day</ext-link>.</p>
      </disp-quote>
      <p>On English Wikipedia, an event can be ‘current’ without being
  <monospace>{current}</monospace>. This contradiction lies at the heart
  of Wikipedia’s temporal regime. When Wikipedia’s English editors
  debated the need for Yapperbot/uncurrenter, they ran straight into the
  contradiction between two different understandings of time. To
  stabilise Wikipedia’s temporal regime, they had to resolve this
  contradiction. As we show below, Wikipedia’s English editors made the
  radical move to try and abolish the present, a path that editors of
  other-language Wikipedias have refused to take.</p>
      <fig>
        <caption>
          <p>Template:Current in Italian, Hindi, English, French,
    Korean and German (as of 14 March 2023)</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/banner_collage.png"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Wikipedia is one of the few places where where the construction of
  a temporal regime can be (almost) directly observed. Unlike other
  prominent social media platforms, Wikipedia is an ‘open’ project,
  every one of whose facets can be publicly altered and debated. The
  encyclopaedia can only be changed in public. Nearly every step in the
  construction of the temporal regime leaves an easily-recovered mark.
  It may appear that an ‘open’ platform such as Wikipedia could never
  tolerate something as closed as a temporal <italic>regime</italic>,
  but as Tkacz
  (<xref alt="2015" rid="ref-tkacz_wikipedia_2015" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>)
  shows, Wikipedia’s openness has not prevented it from developing a
  restrictive ‘frame’ of rules and concepts that govern its activities.
  Quite the contrary. Wikipedia is not only the most open of social
  networks—it is surely also the most highly organised.</p>
      <p>Wikipedia is also a place where ‘technicities of time’ are
  especially prominent. Large parts of the encyclopedia are managed by
  bots such as Yapperbot/uncurrenter, which are powerful actors in
  Wikipedia’s sociotechnical system
  (<xref alt="Niederer and Dijck 2010" rid="ref-niederer_wisdom_2010" ref-type="bibr">Niederer
  and Dijck 2010</xref>;
  <xref alt="Dijck 2013, 137–40" rid="ref-dijck_culture_2013" ref-type="bibr">Dijck
  2013, 137–40</xref>;
  <xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger and Ribes 2010" rid="ref-geiger_work_2010" ref-type="bibr">R.
  Stuart Geiger and Ribes 2010</xref>;
  <xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger and Halfaker 2013" rid="ref-geiger_when_2013" ref-type="bibr">R.
  Stuart Geiger and Halfaker 2013</xref>,
  <xref alt="2017" rid="ref-geiger_operationalizing_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="Tkacz 2015, 111–19" rid="ref-tkacz_wikipedia_2015" ref-type="bibr">Tkacz
  2015, 111–19</xref>;
  <xref alt="Halfaker and Riedl 2012" rid="ref-halfaker_bots_2012" ref-type="bibr">Halfaker
  and Riedl 2012</xref>;
  <xref alt="Livingstone 2016" rid="ref-livingstone_population_2016" ref-type="bibr">Livingstone
  2016</xref>). Bots are best understand as users of the platform,
  rather than as extensions of their human developers. Indeed, Wikipedia
  bots have ordinary user accounts like human Wikipedians, although they
  also have special privileges and their actions are tracked separately
  by the system. Bots incarnate or enact Wikipedia’s culture, as Stuart
  Geiger has revealed in a pathbreaking series of papers
  (<xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger 2009" rid="ref-geiger_social_2009" ref-type="bibr">R.
  Stuart Geiger 2009</xref>,
  <xref alt="2011" rid="ref-geiger_lives_2011" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>,
  <xref alt="2013" rid="ref-geiger_are_2013" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>;
  <xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger 2017" rid="ref-geiger_beyond_2017" ref-type="bibr">R.
  Stuart Geiger 2017</xref>; see also
  <xref alt="Kennedy 2010" rid="ref-kennedy_textual_2010" ref-type="bibr">Kennedy
  2010</xref>). To understand bots, he explains, it is not sufficient to
  read the source code, although there may well be important policies,
  procedures or ideals ‘encoded’ in the source
  (<xref alt="2017, 9" rid="ref-geiger_beyond_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017,
  9</xref>). Instead, it is essential to observe how bots act in the
  wild, and to observe how human users and other bots interact with
  <italic>them</italic>
  (<xref alt="2011" rid="ref-geiger_lives_2011" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>;
  <xref alt="2017" rid="ref-geiger_beyond_2017" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).
  In this spirit, we pursue Yapperbot/uncurrenter through Wikipedia, to
  see how it works and whom it fights to uphold Wikipedia’s temporal
  regime.</p>
      <p>Our discussion falls into four main sections. In
  <xref alt="How to make time" rid="how-to-make-time">How to make
  time</xref>, we present a theory of ‘temporal mapping’ to show how
  temporal regimes can be produced through repetition, representation
  and technicity. In
  <xref alt="Wikipedia time (1): the primacy of the past" rid="wikipedia-time-1-the-primacy-of-the-past">Wikipedia
  time (1): the primacy of the past</xref>, we consider existing
  research into Wikipedia’s temporal regime, and consider the various
  ways that time enters into the encyclopaedia. In
  <xref alt="The birth of the bot that makes history" rid="the-birth-of-the-bot-that-makes-history">The
  birth of the bot that makes history</xref>, we describe the series of
  events that led to Yapperbot/uncurrenter’s creation, and use a range
  of qualitative and quantitiative methods to analyse its contributions
  to Wikipedia. Finally, in
  <xref alt="Wikipedia time (2): encyclopaedia time" rid="wikipedia-time-2-encyclopaedia-time">Wikipedia
  time (2): encyclopaedia time</xref>, we offer our conclusions about
  Wikipedia’s temporal regime, contextualising Wikipedia as one in a
  long line of encyclopaedic projects that attempt to encompass time. We
  conclude that Wikipedia’s temporal regime is <italic>complex regime of
  historicity</italic>. It is <italic>complex</italic> because it is a
  clash of many temporalities, which are contested by the people and
  other actors on the platform. It is <italic>historicist</italic>
  because it attempts to situate its human participants in the process
  of history through literary representation. The example of Wikipedia’s
  <italic>complex historicity</italic> supports the idea that time
  remains contingent. There is no fixed regime of digital time or
  network time. Time is out there for the making.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="how-to-make-time">
      <title>How to make time</title>
      <p>We make temporal regimes by mixing time and space. We map time. The
  crying of the infant, the waxing of the moon, the rising of the dough,
  the coming of the moths, the shadow of the sundial, the alignment of
  the text, the stellar orientation of the standing stones—all are maps,
  which crystallise time in space. Whether this mapping occurs by
  analysis or synthesis depends on your view of time. For Henri Bergson,
  the ‘spatialization’ of time is analytic. Time is fundamentally
  <italic>duration</italic> [<italic>durée</italic>]. Our basic
  experience of time is continuous. When we spatialize time, we divide
  it, for instance when split it into hours and minutes, and map these
  divisions onto the clock
  (<xref alt="1984, 71–72" rid="ref-bergson_oeuvres_1984" ref-type="bibr">1984,
  71–72</xref>). For Arthur Schopenhauer, by contrast, the
  spatialization of time is synthetic. Our basic experience of time is
  discontinuous. Time is an endless series of unique moments:
  ‘Succession is the whole being of time’
  (<xref alt="Schopenhauer 1999, vol. 1" rid="ref-schopenhauer_werke_1999" ref-type="bibr">Schopenhauer
  1999, vol. 1</xref>, p. 37).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref> We
  can only form a conception of the ‘duration’ [<italic>Dauer</italic>]
  of things when time and space are united in the ‘understanding’
  [<italic>Verstand</italic>]
  (<xref alt="1999, vol. 1" rid="ref-schopenhauer_werke_1999" ref-type="bibr">1999,
  vol. 1</xref>, p. 40). Had Schopenhauer experienced the cinema, he
  might have chosen it as his metaphor. From the whirring filmstrip of
  individual moments, we project the movie of life. Bergson rejected the
  cinema as a metaphor for consciousness
  (<xref alt="1984, 752ff" rid="ref-bergson_oeuvres_1984" ref-type="bibr">1984,
  752ff</xref>). For him, the Kantian view of time as succession
  insufficiently distinguishes time from space. To think time as
  succession, we need to use a spatial metaphor such as a ‘line’ or
  ‘chain’, and ‘juxtapose’ time’s moments along it
  (<xref alt="1984, 68" rid="ref-bergson_oeuvres_1984" ref-type="bibr">1984,
  68</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref> A Kantian like
  Schopenhauer might reply that Bergson is too empirical. What makes it
  possible for Bergson to experience time as a non-spatial duration, if
  not the synthetic activity of the understanding?</p>
      <p>Whichever theory of spatialization we adopt, it is clear that there
  are many ways to map time. The time of the wheat is not the time of
  the Twitter feed. The sheer variety of temporal mappings is a key
  theme in the work of Mikhail Bakhtin. In his classic study of the
  ‘chronotope’, Bakhtin argues that different forms of literature are
  defined by their different forms of time
  (<xref alt="1981, 85" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  85</xref>). Greek romance is charactersised by ‘adventure-time’
  (<xref alt="1981, 87" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  87</xref>), modern fiction by ‘historical time’
  (<xref alt="1981, 165" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  165</xref>), Dostoyevsky’s existential novels by ‘mystery- and
  carnvial-time’
  (<xref alt="1981, 249" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  249</xref>). The time-mapping technology in this case is writing.
  Writers shape time with words. Words can shape time literally, for
  instance when Greek romanciers stitch together the moments of
  adventure-time using ‘link-words’ such as ‘suddenly’ or ‘at that
  moment’
  (<xref alt="1981, 92" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  92</xref>). Words can shape time symbolically, for instance when a
  writer portrays the ‘path of life’ as a road
  (<xref alt="1981, 120" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  120</xref>). Bakhtin demonstrates how a technology such as writing can
  constitute different forms of time; indeed, his researches support the
  more radical argument of Bernard Stiegler, who claims that ‘organized
  inorganic beings’ such as novels might be generally
  ‘<italic>constitutive</italic> … of temporality as well as spatiality’
  (<xref alt="1998, 17" rid="ref-stiegler_technics_1998" ref-type="bibr">1998,
  17</xref>). We experience time and space through the maps we make of
  them.</p>
      <p>Maps structure time by structuring attention. The Sunderland
  petitioners in 1800: ‘many people are obliged to be up at all hours of
  the night to attend the tides’ (quoted in
  <xref alt="Thompson 1967, 60" rid="ref-thompson_time_1967" ref-type="bibr">Thompson
  1967, 60</xref>). To <italic>attend</italic>. The tides rise and fall
  (<italic>repetition</italic>). Through their height, they tell the the
  hour, day, month and season (<italic>representation</italic>). They
  are known partly by sight, and partly by moon-phase and tide-chart and
  plumb-line (<italic>technicity</italic>). To attend upon the tides is
  to know not only <italic>what</italic> time it is (high tide, spring),
  but <italic>what kind</italic> of time it is (to depart or return). In
  this way, attention plays a ‘constructive role … in fabricating tools
  and technical ensembles’
  (<xref alt="Hayles 2012, 91" rid="ref-hayles_how_2012" ref-type="bibr">Hayles
  2012, 91</xref>). The boat, the compass, the fishing-line and the
  fisher are fused together by attention on the tides.</p>
      <p>Through the power of attention, temporal <italic>maps</italic> can
  uphold temporal <italic>regimes</italic>. The classic example comes
  from the Industrial Revolution. Thompson
  (<xref alt="1967" rid="ref-thompson_time_1967" ref-type="bibr">1967</xref>)
  memorably describes the scene. As the ‘need for the synchronization of
  labour’ grew, so did the need for ‘[a]ttention to time’
  (<xref alt="Thompson 1967, 70" rid="ref-thompson_time_1967" ref-type="bibr">Thompson
  1967, 70</xref>)—or rather, the need for a particular kind of
  attention, which Thompson calls ‘time-discipline’. Masters used the
  factory clock (a map) to impose time-discipline on their workers (a
  regime). They fiddled with the clock to extract more hours of labour.
  They handed out gold watches for long service. Workers themselves
  would blow a windfall on a watch of their own—for the status, or the
  power? This example demonstrates why the repetition-theory of
  Orlikowski and Yates
  (<xref alt="2002" rid="ref-orlikowski_its_2002" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>)
  must be supplemented by the concepts of representation and technicity.
  The ‘recurrent action’ of factory workers can only be fully explained
  if we include the clock, which represented time as a succession of
  hours and minutes to be spent working, and which legitimated the new
  temporal regime by its (apparent) impersonality.</p>
      <p>Not all temporal maps are as strict or authoritative as Thompson’s
  factory-clock. Theorists of <italic>technicity</italic> observe that
  technical objects vary greatly in their degree of ‘concretization’
  (<xref alt="Stiegler 1998" rid="ref-stiegler_technics_1998" ref-type="bibr">Stiegler
  1998</xref>). Concretization is a process of unification. As a
  technology becomes more concrete, its parts become ‘organs’ that
  ‘function more and more as parts of a whole’
  (<xref alt="Stiegler 1998, 71" rid="ref-stiegler_technics_1998" ref-type="bibr">Stiegler
  1998, 71</xref>). It thus becomes autonomous. It ceases to be a
  ‘utensil’ of a human ‘actor’; it becomes itself an ‘actor’ with human
  ‘operators’
  (<xref alt="Stiegler 1998, 66" rid="ref-stiegler_technics_1998" ref-type="bibr">Stiegler
  1998, 66</xref>). The drying of hops was once regulated by the dryer,
  who touched and smelt the cones to determine the drying-time. The
  dryer relied on comparatively abstract technology (the oast-house and
  its cowl) to regulate the time by regulating the temperature and
  humidity. Today, the dryer is a machine, which determines the
  drying-time autonomously using clocks and sensors. Such a concrete
  technology in effect concretizes time itself. The drying-time is
  nothing but the time it takes for the machine to work.</p>
      <p>In the same way we characterise technicities as
  <italic>concrete</italic> or <italic>abstract</italic>, we can
  characterise repetitions as <italic>regular</italic> or
  <italic>irregular</italic>, and representations as
  <italic>clear</italic> or <italic>vague</italic>. Thompson
  (<xref alt="1967" rid="ref-thompson_time_1967" ref-type="bibr">1967</xref>)
  repeatedly stresses the ‘regularity’ of capitalist work-patterns, as
  opposed to the ‘irregularity’ of work in pre-capitalist temporal
  regimes. While we may reject Thompson’s schematism, we must accept his
  observation that repetition can vary in its lawfulness and
  predictability. The tanpura drones regularly while the sitar wanders
  in endless novelty. In much the same way, a representation of time can
  be clear and bright or vague and suggestive. A modern composer gives
  the tempo in beats per minute, where a Romantic requests the orchestra
  to play <italic>Bewegt, doch nicht schnell</italic>.</p>
      <p>Temporal regimes are seldom unitary. They combine many temporal
  maps to create a ‘multiplicity’
  (<xref alt="Orlikowski and Yates 2002, 687" rid="ref-orlikowski_its_2002" ref-type="bibr">Orlikowski
  and Yates 2002, 687</xref>) or ‘complex’ of temporalities
  (<xref alt="Hayles 2012, 89" rid="ref-hayles_how_2012" ref-type="bibr">Hayles
  2012, 89</xref>). This complexity is especially apparent on the plane
  of representation. Digital media can present many different interfaces
  to time. A Wikipedia article represents time as a connected narrative
  on the ‘Article’ tab, as a list of versions on the ‘View history’ tab,
  as an ongoing debate between editors on the ‘Talk’ tab, as a
  time-series of web hits on the Pageviews tool, as a pie-chart of
  contributions on the XTools interface, as an immutable series of
  transactions in the underlying MYSQL database, and so on. Such
  interfaces form a single unstable ‘complex’ because they are folded
  together by Wikipedia’s various actors. This complexity leads to
  contradiction, which leads to contention, which led, in one case, to
  Yapperbot/uncurrenter.</p>
      <p>In sum, we define a temporal regime as a system of temporal maps
  that structure a particular form of life through the modulation of
  human attention. We can now refine our research questions. How do
  Wikipedians map time? Which mappings are established, which are
  contested, and how does Yapperbot/uncurrenter fit among them? How has
  digital technology changed the nature of temporal mapping?</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="wikipedia-time-1-the-primacy-of-the-past">
      <title>Wikipedia time (1): the primacy of the past</title>
      <p>
        <italic>TODO: Rewrite/adapt</italic>
      </p>
      <p>How does Wikipedia portray the past? Scholars typically give three
  answers. Some argue that Wikipedia produces <italic>history</italic>:
  it represents the past in literary form. Wikipedia history may be more
  “colorful,” “anecdotal” and “factualist” than “professional history,”
  observes Roy Rosenzweig, but history it most certainly is
  (<xref alt="Rosenzweig 2006, 142" rid="ref-rosenzweig_can_2006" ref-type="bibr">Rosenzweig
  2006, 142</xref>). Others argue that Wikipedia articles comprise
  <italic>collective memories</italic> that evoke shared experiences.
  From this perspective, Wikipedia’s Talk pages are more important than
  the articles themselves, and its editors are more important than its
  readers. As Christian Pentzold argues, Wikipedia’s Talk pages are
  non-physical “memory places,” where editors meet to “negotiat[e]” the
  “memorable elements” of their experiences
  (<xref alt="Pentzold 2009, 264" rid="ref-pentzold_fixing_2009" ref-type="bibr">Pentzold
  2009, 264</xref>). Numerous scholars have followed in Pentzold’s wake
  to examine how editors “build” or “form” collective memories in
  Wikipedia
  (<xref alt="Ferron and Massa 2011b" rid="ref-ferron_collective_2011" ref-type="bibr">Ferron
  and Massa 2011b</xref>,
  <xref alt="2011a" rid="ref-ferron_arab_2011" ref-type="bibr">2011a</xref>;
  <xref alt="Porter, Krafft, and Keegan 2020" rid="ref-porter_visual_2020" ref-type="bibr">Porter,
  Krafft, and Keegan 2020</xref>). A third group of scholars argue that
  Wikipedia is a repository of <italic>facts</italic>. Wikipedia may
  well publish works of history and store collective memories, but its
  main role is to produce atomistic facts that are propagated through
  knowledge graphs
  (<xref alt="Ford 2020" rid="ref-ford_rise_2020" ref-type="bibr">Ford
  2020</xref>,
  <xref alt="2022" rid="ref-ford_writing_2022" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>).
  Wikipedia may be <italic>memory</italic> to thousands of editors. It
  may be <italic>history</italic> to millions of readers. But it is mere
  <italic>fact</italic> to billions of search requests and API
  calls.</p>
      <p>These approaches are not mutually exclusive. Search engines,
  readers and editors all produce and consume Wikipedia in different
  ways, and a complete account of the encyclopedia must include them
  all. In which case, we must ask: how are the historical, memorial and
  factual aspects of Wikipedia related?</p>
      <p>One way to approach this question is to focus precisely on the
  <italic>pastness</italic> of history, memory and fact. Pastness is
  central to Wikipedia’s self-definition. “Wikipedia is not a crystal
  ball,” reads
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WP:NOT">a
  famous policy</ext-link>, wherein we also read that Wikipedia is “not
  a newspaper.” It is the pastness of Wikipedia that allows it to
  function simultaneously as history, memory and fact. Pastness is
  obviously a feature of both history and memory: I cannot remember an
  event nor write its history until it has happened. The pastness of
  <italic>fact</italic> is less obvious. Wikipedia contains facts about
  fictional spacecraft, embroidery techniques and the heat death of the
  universe. In what sense can such facts be said to be “past”?</p>
      <p>Wikipedia itself provides an answer in two of its foundational
  policies. According to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:No_original_research">‘No
  Original Research’</ext-link>, no new facts are to be admitted to the
  encyclopaedia. The only allowable facts are—the <italic>old</italic>.
  According to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Neutral_point_of_view">‘Neutral
  Point of View’</ext-link>, no controversial facts are to be admitted
  to the encyclopaedia. The only allowable facts are—the
  <italic>settled</italic>. Facts are geological. Only time can grind
  down the seashells of evidence and bring forth the limestone of
  objectivity. Editors who wish to include new or unsettled facts in the
  encyclopaedia are advised that
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:There_is_no_deadline">‘There
  is no deadline’</ext-link>. <italic>Þæs oferēode; þisses swa
  mæg.</italic> That passed; so may this. Eventually everything is
  past.</p>
      <p>Despite its supposed pastness, Wikipedia is well-known as a source
  of information on current events. It is ‘An Encylopedia with Breaking
  News’
  (<xref alt="Keegan 2019" rid="ref-keegan_encyclopedia_2019" ref-type="bibr">Keegan
  2019</xref>). Current events dominate Wikipedia, accounting for the
  lion’s share of user contributions and page views at any given time
  (<xref alt="Keegan, Gergle, and Contractor 2011" rid="ref-keegan_hot_2011" ref-type="bibr">Keegan,
  Gergle, and Contractor 2011</xref>). Scholars have analysed
  Wikipedia’s coverage of current events in detail. We now know how
  Wikipedia’s editors clash over the nature and definition of current
  events
  (<xref alt="Ford 2022" rid="ref-ford_writing_2022" ref-type="bibr">Ford
  2022</xref>;
  <xref alt="Pentzold 2009" rid="ref-pentzold_fixing_2009" ref-type="bibr">Pentzold
  2009</xref>), how they link current events into larger thematic
  structures
  (<xref alt="Twyman, Keegan, and Shaw 2017" rid="ref-twyman_black_2017" ref-type="bibr">Twyman,
  Keegan, and Shaw 2017</xref>), how they adopt newsroom practices to
  co-ordinate their efforts
  (<xref alt="Avieson 2019" rid="ref-avieson_breaking_2019" ref-type="bibr">Avieson
  2019</xref>), how they revisit old articles to commemorate traumatic
  events
  (<xref alt="Ferron and Massa 2014" rid="ref-ferron_beyond_2014" ref-type="bibr">Ferron
  and Massa 2014</xref>), and how they shape the interpretation of
  events using images
  (<xref alt="Porter, Krafft, and Keegan 2020" rid="ref-porter_visual_2020" ref-type="bibr">Porter,
  Krafft, and Keegan 2020</xref>). One thing we <italic>don’t</italic>
  know is how Wikipedia’s editors decide what is ‘current’. How does
  Wikipedia distinguish the past from the present at the very threshold
  of time? How does it resolve the contradiction between the pastness of
  the encyclopaedia and the presentness of the current?</p>
      <p>Most readers of Wikipedia will have seen what editors do when an
  article trespasses on the present: mark it with one of the available
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Current_event_templates">Current
  Event Templates</ext-link>. The main template is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Current">Template:Current</ext-link>,
  which at the time of writing is available on 116 language editions of
  Wikipedia. When the template is added to an article, a familiar banner
  appears at the top of the page (Figure ), and the article is
  automatically added to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Current_events">Category:Current
  Events</ext-link> or a related category. Each language edition has its
  own distinct version of Template:Current, and may also sport a range
  of related Templates. French Wikipedia, for instance, distinguishes
  ‘Événements en cours’ [ongoing events] from ‘Événements récents’
  [recent events] in its
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mod%C3%A8le:%C3%89v%C3%A9nement_en_cours">main
  template</ext-link>, and provides several related templates such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mod%C3%A8le:Bataille_en_cours">Modèle:Bataille
  en cours</ext-link> [Template:Ongoing battle] and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mod%C3%A8le:Mort_r%C3%A9cente">Modèle:Mort
  récente</ext-link> [Template:Recent death]. German Wikipedia, by
  contrast, has only a single
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vorlage:Laufendes_Ereignis">Current
  Events template</ext-link>, but it is customisable, so that editors
  can replace the phrase “aktuelles Ereignis” [current event] in the
  banner with a more specific description such as “die derzeitige
  Sportveranstaltung” [the ongoing sporting event].</p>
      <p>New twist in the tale: a user ‘killed’ Yapperbot/uncurrent on
  24/4/2023 because
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=1151461527&amp;oldid=986550108&amp;title=User%3AYapperbot%2Fkill%2FUncurrenter">they
  complained it had removed {{current}} from a current
  event</ext-link>.</p>
      <p>On the surface, Template:Current might seem like a simple
  phenomenon. Editors mark an article when it is “current,” then remove
  the template when its currency is ended. Avieson
  (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-avieson_breaking_2019" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)
  likens Template:Current to the “live” icon on a newspaper blog or
  television news. While Template:Current is present, the article
  functions as live coverage; when the template is removed, the article
  gradually becomes encyclopaedic.</p>
      <p>But the use of Template:Current is not simple, and has vexed
  Wikipedia’s editors for years. Avieson
  (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-avieson_breaking_2019" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)
  herself grapples with the problem. Although she argues for a
  distinction between “news” and “encyclopaedias,” she also observes
  that Wikipedia’s coverage of current events “blurs the boundaries of
  both news and temporality.” These blurred boundaries are a problem for
  Wikipedia’s editors, and editors in different langauges have clarified
  the distinction between past, present and future in different ways. In
  this context, English Wikipedia is extremist. Unlike other language
  editions, English Wikipedia strictly polices the use of
  Template:Current with a bot:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Yapperbot">Yapperbot/uncurrenter</ext-link>.
  Yapperbot/uncurrenter scans English Wikipedia hourly, examining every
  article that includes Template:Current and deleting the template if
  the article has not been edited in the last five hours. English
  Wikipedia is also one of the few larger language editions without a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Future">Template:Future</ext-link>
  to mark events that have yet to occur. English Wikipedia deleted
  Template:Future in 2009 after an official process, and several
  attempts to resurrect the template have foundered. Meanwhile French,
  Italian, Bengali, Chinese and 51 other-language Wikipedias maintain a
  Template:Future.</p>
      <p>Why does practice vary across the different language editions? What
  led to the extremely strict approach of English Wikipedia, in which
  Template:Current is ruthlessly policed by an artificial agent, and the
  future is not explicitly marked? What can this tell us about
  Wikipedia’s “temporal regime”
  (<xref alt="Assmann 2020" rid="ref-assmann_is_2020" ref-type="bibr">Assmann
  2020</xref>)?</p>
      <p>We try to answer these questions by focussing on
  Yapperbot/uncurrenter. We describe the history of Template:Current and
  recount the debates that led to the bot’s creation. We then examine
  Yapperbot/uncurrenter’s contributions to English Wikipedia, comparing
  its practice with the practice of human editors on English Wikipedia
  and other-language Wikipedias.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="the-birth-of-the-bot-that-makes-history">
      <title>The birth of the bot that makes history</title>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p><italic>Qualitative methods:</italic> Reading the talk pages,
      bot approval etc. that led to the creation of
      Yapperbot/uncurrenter</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><italic>Quantitative methods:</italic> Comparison of
      Yapperbot/uncurrenter with humans who have policed
      Template:Current using wikkitidy
      (<xref alt="Falk 2023" rid="ref-falk_wikkitidy_2023" ref-type="bibr">Falk
      2023</xref>) and the tidyverse
      (<xref alt="Wickham et al. 2019" rid="ref-wickham_welcome_2019" ref-type="bibr">Wickham
      et al. 2019</xref>).</p>
        </list-item>
        <list-item>
          <p><italic>Methodology:</italic> Trace ethnography
      (<xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger and Ribes 2011" rid="ref-geiger_trace_2011" ref-type="bibr">R.
      Stuart Geiger and Ribes 2011</xref>); ethnography of algorithmic
      systems
      (<xref alt="Seaver 2017" rid="ref-seaver_algorithms_2017" ref-type="bibr">Seaver
      2017</xref>;
      <xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger 2017" rid="ref-geiger_beyond_2017" ref-type="bibr">R.
      Stuart Geiger 2017</xref>).</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
      <p>
        <italic>How did `Yapperbot/uncurrenter’ come about? What were the
  debates and discussions of the editors? What was the perceived problem
  the bot was supposed to fix?</italic>
      </p>
      <p>
        <italic>What does the bot actually do? How does that compare with
  what it is supposed to do?</italic>
      </p>
      <p>How many pages is yapperbot uncurrenting per day?</p>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="the-bot-that-makes-history_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png"/>
      <p>What was happening on that day it uncurrented 45 pages?</p>
      <preformat># A tibble: 45 × 3
     pageid title                                            timestamp          
      &lt;dbl&gt; &lt;chr&gt;                                            &lt;dttm&gt;             
 1 63362621 COVID-19 pandemic in Ethiopia                    2020-10-21 23:00:28
 2 63431783 COVID-19 pandemic in Northern Ireland            2020-10-21 22:00:48
 3 63181042 COVID-19 pandemic in Europe                      2020-10-21 22:00:41
 4 63178596 COVID-19 pandemic in Hong Kong                   2020-10-21 22:00:38
 5 63313047 COVID-19 pandemic in Moldova                     2020-10-21 21:00:43
 6 63239190 COVID-19 pandemic in Sweden                      2020-10-21 21:00:37
 7 64307024 Timeline of the COVID-19 pandemic in October 20… 2020-10-21 20:00:49
 8 63395521 COVID-19 pandemic in Sarawak                     2020-10-21 20:00:45
 9 63391509 COVID-19 pandemic in Quebec                      2020-10-21 20:00:39
10 63389195 COVID-19 pandemic in Sabah                       2020-10-21 20:00:36
# ℹ 35 more rows</preformat>
      <p>How often does Yapperbot have to remove the template more than
  once?</p>
      <preformat># A tibble: 7 × 2
  count num_pages
  &lt;int&gt;     &lt;int&gt;
1     1      1236
2     2       133
3     3        23
4     4         9
5     5         4
6     6         2
7     9         1</preformat>
      <p>Which page had to be uncurrented nine times?</p>
      <preformat># A tibble: 7 × 3
# Groups:   pageid [7]
    pageid title                                            count
     &lt;dbl&gt; &lt;chr&gt;                                            &lt;int&gt;
1 70168267 Siege of Mariupol                                    9
2 65760352 Tigray War                                           6
3 70161957 Siege of Chernihiv                                   6
4 64399515 2020–2021 Belarusian protests                        5
5 70157964 Timeline of the 2022 Russian invasion of Ukraine     5
6 70160923 Battle of Kharkiv (2022)                             5
7 70809573 2022–2023 monkeypox outbreak                         5</preformat>
    </sec>
    <sec id="wikipedia-time-2-encyclopaedia-time">
      <title>Wikipedia time (2): encyclopaedia time</title>
      <p>
        <italic>Compared to other temporal regimes</italic>
      </p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title/>
      <ref id="ref-porter_visual_2020">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Porter</surname>
              <given-names>Emily</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krafft</surname>
              <given-names>P. M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keegan</surname>
              <given-names>Brian</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Visual Narratives and Collective Memory across Peer-Produced Accounts of Contested Sociopolitical Events</article-title>
          <source>ACM Transactions on Social Computing</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2020-02">2020</year>
          <month>02</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-09">2023</year>
            <month>01</month>
            <day>09</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <issn>2469-7818</issn>
          <uri>http://doi.org/10.1145/3373147</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/3373147</pub-id>
          <fpage>4:1</fpage>
          <lpage>4:20</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-twyman_black_2017">
        <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Twyman</surname>
              <given-names>Marlon</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Keegan</surname>
              <given-names>Brian C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shaw</surname>
              <given-names>Aaron</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Black Lives Matter in Wikipedia: Collaboration and Collective Memory around Online Social Movements</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 2017 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017-02">2017</year>
          <month>02</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-03">2023</year>
            <month>01</month>
            <day>03</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <uri>http://arxiv.org/abs/1611.01257</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2998181.2998232</pub-id>
          <fpage>1400</fpage>
          <lpage>1412</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-pentzold_fixing_2009">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pentzold</surname>
              <given-names>Christian</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fixing the floating gap: The online encyclopaedia Wikipedia as a global memory place</article-title>
          <source>Memory Studies</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2009-05">2009</year>
          <month>05</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-03">2023</year>
            <month>01</month>
            <day>03</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <issn>1750-6980, 1750-6999</issn>
          <uri>http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1750698008102055</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1750698008102055</pub-id>
          <fpage>255</fpage>
          <lpage>272</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-castells_rise_2010">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Castells</surname>
              <given-names>Manuel</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The rise of the network society</source>
          <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Chichester, West Sussex ; Malden, MA</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
          <edition>2nd ed., with a new pref</edition>
          <isbn>978-1-4051-9686-4</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-ford_writing_2022">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ford</surname>
              <given-names>Heather</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Writing the revolution: Wikipedia and the survival of facts in the digital age</source>
          <publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year>
          <isbn>978-0-262-04629-9</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-rosenzweig_can_2006">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
              <given-names>Roy</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Can History Be Open Source? Wikipedia and the Future of the Past</article-title>
          <source>The Journal of American History</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-23">2023</year>
            <month>01</month>
            <day>23</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <issn>0021-8723</issn>
          <uri>http://www.jstor.org/stable/4486062</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/4486062</pub-id>
          <fpage>117</fpage>
          <lpage>146</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-tkacz_wikipedia_2015">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tkacz</surname>
              <given-names>Nathaniel</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Wikipedia and the politics of openness</source>
          <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Chicago ; London</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
          <isbn>978-0-226-19227-7 978-0-226-19230-7</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-wajcman_pressed_2015">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wajcman</surname>
              <given-names>Judy</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Pressed for time: The acceleration of life in digital capitalism</source>
          <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
          <isbn>978-0-226-19650-3</isbn>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7208/9780226196503</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-keegan_encyclopedia_2019">
        <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Keegan</surname>
              <given-names>Brian</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An encyclopedia with breaking news</article-title>
          <source>Wikipedia@ 20: Stories of an Incomplete Revolution</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Reagle</surname>
              <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koerner</surname>
              <given-names>Jackie</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Mass</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
          <uri>https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/12366.003.0007</uri>
          <fpage>55</fpage>
          <lpage>70</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-avieson_breaking_2019">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Avieson</surname>
              <given-names>Bunty</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Breaking news on Wikipedia: Collaborating, collating and competing</article-title>
          <source>First Monday</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2019-04">2019</year>
          <month>04</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-30">2023</year>
            <month>01</month>
            <day>30</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <issn>1396-0466</issn>
          <uri>https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/9530</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5210/fm.v24i5.9530</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-keegan_hot_2011">
        <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Keegan</surname>
              <given-names>Brian</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gergle</surname>
              <given-names>Darren</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Contractor</surname>
              <given-names>Noshir</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hot off the wiki: Dynamics, practices, and structures in Wikipedia’s coverage of the Tōhoku catastrophes</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 7th International Symposium on Wikis and Open Collaboration</source>
          <publisher-name>ACM</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Mountain View California</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2011-10">2011</year>
          <month>10</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-30">2023</year>
            <month>01</month>
            <day>30</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <isbn>978-1-4503-0909-7</isbn>
          <uri>https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/2038558.2038577</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2038558.2038577</pub-id>
          <fpage>105</fpage>
          <lpage>113</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-ferron_arab_2011">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferron</surname>
              <given-names>Michela</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Massa</surname>
              <given-names>Paolo</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Arab Spring wikirevolutions: Wikipedia as a lens for studying the real-time formation of collective memories of revolutions</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Communication</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>20</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-ferron_beyond_2014">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferron</surname>
              <given-names>Michela</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Massa</surname>
              <given-names>Paolo</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Beyond the encyclopedia: Collective memories in Wikipedia</article-title>
          <source>Memory Studies</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <lpage>45</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-gumbrecht_our_2014">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gumbrecht</surname>
              <given-names>Hans Ulrich</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Our broad present: Time and contemporary culture</source>
          <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
          <isbn>978-0-231-16360-6 978-0-231-16361-3</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-ferron_collective_2011">
        <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferron</surname>
              <given-names>Michela</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Massa</surname>
              <given-names>Paolo</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Collective memory building in Wikipedia: The case of North African uprisings</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 7th International Symposium on Wikis and Open Collaboration</source>
          <publisher-name>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2011-10">2011</year>
          <month>10</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-26">2023</year>
            <month>02</month>
            <day>26</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <isbn>978-1-4503-0909-7</isbn>
          <uri>https://doi.org/10.1145/2038558.2038578</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2038558.2038578</pub-id>
          <fpage>114</fpage>
          <lpage>123</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-ford_rise_2020">
        <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ford</surname>
              <given-names>Heather</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rise of the Underdog</article-title>
          <source>Wikipedia@20: Stories of an Incomplete Revolution</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Reagle</surname>
              <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koerner</surname>
              <given-names>Jackie</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Mass</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2020-10">2020</year>
          <month>10</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-27">2023</year>
            <month>02</month>
            <day>27</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <uri>https://direct.mit.edu/books/book/4956/chapter/1879827/Rise-of-the-Underdog</uri>
          <fpage>189</fpage>
          <lpage>201</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-assmann_is_2020">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Assmann</surname>
              <given-names>Aleida</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Is Time out of Joint?: On the Rise and Fall of the Modern Time Regime</source>
          <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Ithaca, UNITED STATES</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-26">2023</year>
            <month>01</month>
            <day>26</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <isbn>978-1-5017-4245-3</isbn>
          <uri>http://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/uts/detail.action?docID=5964894</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-geiger_when_2013">
        <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geiger</surname>
              <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halfaker</surname>
              <given-names>Aaron</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>When the levee breaks: Without bots, what happens to Wikipedia’s quality control processes?</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 9th International Symposium on Open Collaboration</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-geiger_work_2010">
        <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geiger</surname>
              <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ribes</surname>
              <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The work of sustaining order in Wikipedia: The banning of a vandal</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 2010 ACM conference on Computer supported cooperative work</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
          <fpage>117</fpage>
          <lpage>126</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-geiger_are_2013">
        <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geiger</surname>
              <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Are computers merely" supporting" cooperative work: Towards an ethnography of bot development</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 2013 conference on Computer supported cooperative work companion</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
          <fpage>51</fpage>
          <lpage>56</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-geiger_social_2009">
        <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geiger</surname>
              <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The social roles of bots and assisted editing programs</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the 5th International Symposium on Wikis and Open Collaboration</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>2</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-geiger_lives_2011">
        <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geiger</surname>
              <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The lives of bots</article-title>
          <source>Critical Point of View: A Wikipedia Reader</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Lovink</surname>
              <given-names>Geert</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tkacz</surname>
              <given-names>Nathaniel</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-name>Amsterdam</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Institute of Network Cultures</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
          <fpage>78</fpage>
          <lpage>93</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-geiger_operationalizing_2017">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geiger</surname>
              <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halfaker</surname>
              <given-names>Aaron</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Operationalizing conflict and cooperation between automated software agents in wikipedia: A replication and expansion of’even good bots fight’</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>CSCW</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>33</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-geiger_beyond_2017">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geiger</surname>
              <given-names>R Stuart</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Beyond opening up the black box: Investigating the role of algorithmic systems in Wikipedian organizational culture</article-title>
          <source>Big Data &amp; Society</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017-12">2017</year>
          <month>12</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-28">2023</year>
            <month>02</month>
            <day>28</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <issn>2053-9517, 2053-9517</issn>
          <uri>http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/2053951717730735</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2053951717730735</pub-id>
          <fpage>205395171773073</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-niederer_wisdom_2010">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Niederer</surname>
              <given-names>Sabine</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dijck</surname>
              <given-names>José van</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wisdom of the crowd or technicity of content? Wikipedia as a sociotechnical system</article-title>
          <source>New Media &amp; Society</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2010-12">2010</year>
          <month>12</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-28">2023</year>
            <month>02</month>
            <day>28</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <issn>1461-4448</issn>
          <uri>https://doi.org/10.1177/1461444810365297</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1461444810365297</pub-id>
          <fpage>1368</fpage>
          <lpage>1387</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-halfaker_bots_2012">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Halfaker</surname>
              <given-names>Aaron</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riedl</surname>
              <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bots and Cyborgs: Wikipedia’s Immune System</article-title>
          <source>Computer</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2012-03">2012</year>
          <month>03</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-28">2023</year>
            <month>02</month>
            <day>28</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <issn>0018-9162</issn>
          <uri>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6163451/</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/MC.2012.82</pub-id>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>82</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-seaver_algorithms_2017">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seaver</surname>
              <given-names>Nick</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Algorithms as culture: Some tactics for the ethnography of algorithmic systems</article-title>
          <source>Big data &amp; society</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>2053951717738104</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-dijck_culture_2013">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dijck</surname>
              <given-names>José van</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The culture of connectivity: A critical history of social media</source>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Oxford ; New York</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
          <isbn>978-0-19-997077-3 978-0-19-997078-0</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-kennedy_textual_2010">
        <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kennedy</surname>
              <given-names>Krista</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Textual Machinery: Authorial Agency and Bot-Written Texts in Wikipedia</article-title>
          <source>The Responsibilities of Rhetoric</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>Michelle</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warnick</surname>
              <given-names>Barbara</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-name>Waveland</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Long Grove, Illinois</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
          <uri>https://surface.syr.edu/wp/1</uri>
          <fpage>303</fpage>
          <lpage>309</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-livingstone_population_2016">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Livingstone</surname>
              <given-names>Randall M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Population automation: An interview with Wikipedia bot pioneer Ram-Man</article-title>
          <source>First Monday</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2016-01">2016</year>
          <month>01</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-28">2023</year>
            <month>02</month>
            <day>28</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <issn>1396-0466</issn>
          <uri>https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/6027</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5210/fm.v21i1.6027</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-hartog_regimes_2017">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hartog</surname>
              <given-names>François</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Regimes of historicity: Presentism and experiences of time</source>
          <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
          <edition>Paperback edition</edition>
          <isbn>978-0-231-16377-4</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-geiger_trace_2011">
        <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Geiger</surname>
              <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ribes</surname>
              <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Trace Ethnography: Following Coordination through Documentary Practices</article-title>
          <source>2011 44th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2011-01">2011</year>
          <month>01</month>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/HICSS.2011.455</pub-id>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-wickham_welcome_2019">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wickham</surname>
              <given-names>Hadley</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Averick</surname>
              <given-names>Mara</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bryan</surname>
              <given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>Winston</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McGowan</surname>
              <given-names>Lucy D’Agostino</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>François</surname>
              <given-names>Romain</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grolemund</surname>
              <given-names>Garrett</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>Alex</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henry</surname>
              <given-names>Lionel</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hester</surname>
              <given-names>Jim</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuhn</surname>
              <given-names>Max</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pedersen</surname>
              <given-names>Thomas Lin</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>Evan</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bache</surname>
              <given-names>Stephan Milton</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Müller</surname>
              <given-names>Kirill</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ooms</surname>
              <given-names>Jeroen</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seidel</surname>
              <given-names>Dana Paige</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spinu</surname>
              <given-names>Vitalie</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takahashi</surname>
              <given-names>Kohske</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vaughan</surname>
              <given-names>Davis</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilke</surname>
              <given-names>Claus</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Woo</surname>
              <given-names>Kara</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yutani</surname>
              <given-names>Hiroaki</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Welcome to the Tidyverse</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Open Source Software</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2019-11">2019</year>
          <month>11</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-03-27">2023</year>
            <month>03</month>
            <day>27</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <issue>43</issue>
          <issn>2475-9066</issn>
          <uri>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.01686</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01686</pub-id>
          <fpage>1686</fpage>
          <lpage/>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-falk_wikkitidy_2023">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Falk</surname>
              <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Wikkitidy: Tidy analysis of Wikipedia in R</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year>
          <uri>https://wikihistories.github.io/wikkitidy/</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-orlikowski_its_2002">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Orlikowski</surname>
              <given-names>Wanda J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yates</surname>
              <given-names>JoAnne</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>It’s about time: Temporal structuring in organizations</article-title>
          <source>Organization Science</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2002-12">2002</year>
          <month>12</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-03-28">2023</year>
            <month>03</month>
            <day>28</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <issn>10477039</issn>
          <uri>https://www.proquest.com/docview/213829873/abstract/57070C934917444CPQ/1</uri>
          <fpage>684</fpage>
          <lpage>700</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-thompson_time_1967">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>E. P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Time, Work-Discipline, and Industrial Capitalism</article-title>
          <source>Past &amp; Present</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="1967">1967</year>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2023-03-31">2023</year>
            <month>03</month>
            <day>31</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <issue>38</issue>
          <issn>0031-2746</issn>
          <uri>https://www.jstor.org/stable/649749</uri>
          <fpage>56</fpage>
          <lpage>97</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-bergson_oeuvres_1984">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bergson</surname>
              <given-names>Henri</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Œuvres</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Robinet</surname>
              <given-names>André</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-name>Presses universitaires de France</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="1984">1984</year>
          <edition>4e</edition>
          <isbn>978-2-13-038495-3</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bakhtin</surname>
              <given-names>Mikhail</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The Dialogic Imagination: Four Essays</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Holquist</surname>
              <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-name>University of Texas Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="1981">1981</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-stiegler_technics_1998">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stiegler</surname>
              <given-names>Bernard</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Technics and time</source>
          <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Stanford, Calif</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year>
          <isbn>978-0-8047-3040-2 978-0-8047-3041-9 978-0-8047-3012-9</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-schopenhauer_werke_1999">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schopenhauer</surname>
              <given-names>Arthur</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Werke in 5 Bänden mit einem Beibuch</source>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Lütkehaus</surname>
              <given-names>Ludger</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-name>Haffmans Verlag</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year>
          <edition>2</edition>
          <isbn>978-3-96022-011-4</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-hayles_how_2012">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hayles</surname>
              <given-names>N. Katherine</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>How we think: Digital media and contemporary technogenesis</source>
          <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Chicago ; London</publisher-loc>
          <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
          <isbn>978-0-226-32140-0 978-0-226-32142-4</isbn>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn1">
        <label>1</label>
        <p>Succession ist das ganze Wesen der Zeit.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn2">
        <label>2</label>
        <p>In fact, Bergson distinguishes ‘la succession
    pure’ from ‘la succession se développant en espace’; he identifies
    Kantian succession as the second kind
    (<xref alt="1984, 151" rid="ref-bergson_oeuvres_1984" ref-type="bibr">1984,
    151</xref>).</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
  <sub-article article-type="notebook" id="nb-2-nb-article">
    <front-stub>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The bot that makes history</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0001-9261-8390</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Falk</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Michael Falk</string-name>
          <email>michael.falk@unimelb.edu.au</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1-nb-article">a</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1-nb-article">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-3500-9772</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ford</surname>
            <given-names>Heather</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Heather Ford</string-name>
          <email>heather.ford@uts.edu.au</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2-nb-article">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-8304-7108</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Pietsch</surname>
            <given-names>Tamson</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Tamson Pietsch</string-name>
          <email>tamson.pietsch@uts.edu.au</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2-nb-article">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-5796-4105</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Tkacz</surname>
            <given-names>Nathaniel</given-names>
          </name>
          <string-name>Nathaniel Tkacz</string-name>
          <email>n.tkacz@gold.ac.uk</email>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3-nb-article">c</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff-1-nb-article">
        <institution-wrap>
          <institution>University of Melbourne</institution>
        </institution-wrap>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff-2-nb-article">
        <institution-wrap>
          <institution>University of Technology, Sydney</institution>
        </institution-wrap>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff-3-nb-article">
        <institution-wrap>
          <institution>Goldsmiths, University of London</institution>
        </institution-wrap>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor-1-nb-article">michael.falk@unimelb.edu.au</corresp>
      </author-notes>
    </front-stub>
    <body>
      <sec id="nb-code-cell-1-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-code">
        <code language="r script">knitr::opts_chunk$set(echo = FALSE, out.width = "100%")

library(tidyverse)</code>
        <sec id="nb-code-cell-1-output-0-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-output">
          <preformat>── Attaching core tidyverse packages ──────────────────────── tidyverse 2.0.0 ──
✔ dplyr     1.1.4     ✔ readr     2.1.5
✔ forcats   1.0.0     ✔ stringr   1.5.1
✔ ggplot2   3.5.1     ✔ tibble    3.2.1
✔ lubridate 1.9.3     ✔ tidyr     1.3.1
✔ purrr     1.0.2     
── Conflicts ────────────────────────────────────────── tidyverse_conflicts() ──
✖ dplyr::filter() masks stats::filter()
✖ dplyr::lag()    masks stats::lag()
ℹ Use the conflicted package (&lt;http://conflicted.r-lib.org/&gt;) to force all conflicts to become errors</preformat>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="introduction-wikipedia-and-the-technicity-of-time-nb-article">
        <title>Introduction: Wikipedia and The Technicity of Time</title>
        <p>Time is a supple medium. It winds itself into many shapes. It
  surges through the heartwood. It lies upon the bark. It carves rock
  and unfolds in song. It creates myriad structures, then entropically
  destroys them. It races, dallies, recurs, reverses, accelerates,
  splits and stops.</p>
        <p>Despite its suppleness, time has definite characteristics. It forms
  rhythms. It weaves people and plants and animals into lives and
  seasons. It founds eras.</p>
        <p>What are the characteristics of time in the digital era? The
  question has been a major preoccupation for humanists and social
  scientists in the twenty-first century. Theorists in many disciplines
  have argued that ‘presentism’ is the dominant ‘temporal regime’ of the
  twenty-first century
  (<xref alt="Assmann 2020" rid="ref-assmann_is_2020-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Assmann
  2020</xref>;
  <xref alt="Hartog 2017" rid="ref-hartog_regimes_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Hartog
  2017</xref>). We inhabit a ‘broad present’
  (<xref alt="Gumbrecht 2014" rid="ref-gumbrecht_our_2014-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Gumbrecht
  2014</xref>) or a ‘timeless time’
  (<xref alt="Castells 2010" rid="ref-castells_rise_2010-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Castells
  2010</xref>) in which big data and frictionless communication have
  conspired with the cult of memory to abolish the future and bring the
  past into the present. We live in a rubble-world of accumulating fact.
  Other theorists have diagnosed the problem as ‘temporal acceleration’.
  We experience time as running ever faster, argues Wajcman
  (<xref alt="2015, 77" rid="ref-wajcman_pressed_2015-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2015,
  77</xref>), because it has become ‘deroutinized’. We are trapped in
  the present because we are present in so many places at once: on the
  phone to daycare while picking up dinner ingredients in the
  supermarket on our lunchbreak at work. Digital media are the
  handmaidens of post-industrial capitalism. Without them, we would be
  unable to maintain the modicum of order we currently enjoy.</p>
        <p>A weakness of many theories of temporality is their focus on the
  <italic>products</italic> rather than the <italic>production</italic>
  of temporal regimes. To characterise a temporal regime, the theorist
  considers some cultural products, such as literary texts
  (<xref alt="Gumbrecht 2014" rid="ref-gumbrecht_our_2014-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Gumbrecht
  2014</xref>;
  <xref alt="Hartog 2017" rid="ref-hartog_regimes_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Hartog
  2017</xref>) or work-time statistics
  (<xref alt="Castells 2010" rid="ref-castells_rise_2010-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Castells
  2010</xref>) and tries to determine what kind of temporal regime those
  products represent. Such accounts necessarily raise the question: how
  is it possible to erect a temporal regime in the first place? A
  compelling answer is given by Orlikowski and Yates
  (<xref alt="2002" rid="ref-orlikowski_its_2002-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>),
  who argue that the temporal regime of an organisation is produced by
  the ‘practices’ of its members. Such practices can modify a temporal
  regime ‘implicitly’ or ‘explicitly’
  (<xref alt="2002, 687" rid="ref-orlikowski_its_2002-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2002,
  687</xref>), though in either case the key force of change is
  <italic>repetition</italic>, or ‘recurrent action’
  (<xref alt="2002, 696" rid="ref-orlikowski_its_2002-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2002,
  696</xref>). Temporal regimes are rhythmical. They are produced by the
  recurrent actions of people, who learn to act in concert as the
  members of an orchestra.</p>
        <p>In this paper, we build on Orlikowski and Yates’s theory of
  temporal structuration to describe the temporal regime of Wikipedia.
  We show that to explain Wikipedia’s temporal regime, it is necessary
  to supplement Orlikowski and Yates’s theory of
  <italic>repetition</italic> with a theory of time’s
  <italic>representation</italic> and its <italic>technicity</italic>.
  Only by accounting for these three aspects of time can we adequately
  answer our central questions: (1) what is Wikipedia time? and (2) what
  can it tell us about digital time more broadly?</p>
        <p>Our central case study is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Yapperbot">Yapperbot/uncurrenter</ext-link>,
  a ‘bot’ or computer program that polices the barrier between past and
  present on English Wikipedia. We situate Yapperbot/uncurrenter in
  Wikipedia’s broader sociotechnical systems. We examine how it
  interacts with human editors. We show how it fits into Wikipedia’s
  complex array of interfaces and data streams. We present
  Yapperbot/uncurrenter as a prime example of the ‘technicity of time’.
  It is a technology that attempts to make time concrete, to freeze it
  into an object. Yapperbot/uncurrenter is like the master’s clock in an
  eighteenth-century factory. It ticks regularly
  (<italic>repetition</italic>), shows the time
  (<italic>representation</italic>) and acts impersonally
  (<italic>technicity</italic>).</p>
        <p>Yapperbot/uncurrenter performs a single, simple task. Each hour, it
  scans English Wikipedia, finding every article that ‘transcludes’
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Current">Template:Current</ext-link>.
  If the article has not been edited in over five hours, it deletes the
  template.</p>
        <p>A ‘template’ is a microprogram that peforms a common task. In the
  case of Template:Current, the editor inserts the code
  <monospace>{current}</monospace> into an article. This adds a warning
  banner to the article (Figure ), and automatically adds the article to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Current_events">Category:Current_events</ext-link>.
  When Yapperbot/uncurrenter deletes the template, the banner
  disappears, as does the article’s categorisation as a ‘current event’.
  This would seem to consign the article to the past. But here lies the
  first twist in the tale. When Yapperbot/uncurrenter deletes
  Template:Current, it leaves an oddly contradictory message in the
  article’s edit history:</p>
        <disp-quote>
          <p>Auto-removing {{current}} - no edits in 5hrs+. The event may
    still be current, but
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Current">the
    {{current}} template is designed only for articles which many
    editors are editing, and is usually up for less than a
    day</ext-link>.</p>
        </disp-quote>
        <p>On English Wikipedia, an event can be ‘current’ without being
  <monospace>{current}</monospace>. This contradiction lies at the heart
  of Wikipedia’s temporal regime. When Wikipedia’s English editors
  debated the need for Yapperbot/uncurrenter, they ran straight into the
  contradiction between two different understandings of time. To
  stabilise Wikipedia’s temporal regime, they had to resolve this
  contradiction. As we show below, Wikipedia’s English editors made the
  radical move to try and abolish the present, a path that editors of
  other-language Wikipedias have refused to take.</p>
        <sec id="nb-code-cell-2-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-code">
          <code language="r script">knitr::include_graphics("images/banner_collage.png")</code>
          <fig>
            <caption>
              <p>Template:Current in Italian, Hindi, English, French,
    Korean and German (as of 14 March 2023)</p>
            </caption>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/banner_collage.png"/>
          </fig>
        </sec>
        <p>Wikipedia is one of the few places where where the construction of
  a temporal regime can be (almost) directly observed. Unlike other
  prominent social media platforms, Wikipedia is an ‘open’ project,
  every one of whose facets can be publicly altered and debated. The
  encyclopaedia can only be changed in public. Nearly every step in the
  construction of the temporal regime leaves an easily-recovered mark.
  It may appear that an ‘open’ platform such as Wikipedia could never
  tolerate something as closed as a temporal <italic>regime</italic>,
  but as Tkacz
  (<xref alt="2015" rid="ref-tkacz_wikipedia_2015-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>)
  shows, Wikipedia’s openness has not prevented it from developing a
  restrictive ‘frame’ of rules and concepts that govern its activities.
  Quite the contrary. Wikipedia is not only the most open of social
  networks—it is surely also the most highly organised.</p>
        <p>Wikipedia is also a place where ‘technicities of time’ are
  especially prominent. Large parts of the encyclopedia are managed by
  bots such as Yapperbot/uncurrenter, which are powerful actors in
  Wikipedia’s sociotechnical system
  (<xref alt="Niederer and Dijck 2010" rid="ref-niederer_wisdom_2010-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Niederer
  and Dijck 2010</xref>;
  <xref alt="Dijck 2013, 137–40" rid="ref-dijck_culture_2013-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Dijck
  2013, 137–40</xref>;
  <xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger and Ribes 2010" rid="ref-geiger_work_2010-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">R.
  Stuart Geiger and Ribes 2010</xref>;
  <xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger and Halfaker 2013" rid="ref-geiger_when_2013-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">R.
  Stuart Geiger and Halfaker 2013</xref>,
  <xref alt="2017" rid="ref-geiger_operationalizing_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>;
  <xref alt="Tkacz 2015, 111–19" rid="ref-tkacz_wikipedia_2015-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Tkacz
  2015, 111–19</xref>;
  <xref alt="Halfaker and Riedl 2012" rid="ref-halfaker_bots_2012-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Halfaker
  and Riedl 2012</xref>;
  <xref alt="Livingstone 2016" rid="ref-livingstone_population_2016-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Livingstone
  2016</xref>). Bots are best understand as users of the platform,
  rather than as extensions of their human developers. Indeed, Wikipedia
  bots have ordinary user accounts like human Wikipedians, although they
  also have special privileges and their actions are tracked separately
  by the system. Bots incarnate or enact Wikipedia’s culture, as Stuart
  Geiger has revealed in a pathbreaking series of papers
  (<xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger 2009" rid="ref-geiger_social_2009-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">R.
  Stuart Geiger 2009</xref>,
  <xref alt="2011" rid="ref-geiger_lives_2011-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>,
  <xref alt="2013" rid="ref-geiger_are_2013-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>;
  <xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger 2017" rid="ref-geiger_beyond_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">R.
  Stuart Geiger 2017</xref>; see also
  <xref alt="Kennedy 2010" rid="ref-kennedy_textual_2010-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Kennedy
  2010</xref>). To understand bots, he explains, it is not sufficient to
  read the source code, although there may well be important policies,
  procedures or ideals ‘encoded’ in the source
  (<xref alt="2017, 9" rid="ref-geiger_beyond_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2017,
  9</xref>). Instead, it is essential to observe how bots act in the
  wild, and to observe how human users and other bots interact with
  <italic>them</italic>
  (<xref alt="2011" rid="ref-geiger_lives_2011-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>;
  <xref alt="2017" rid="ref-geiger_beyond_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).
  In this spirit, we pursue Yapperbot/uncurrenter through Wikipedia, to
  see how it works and whom it fights to uphold Wikipedia’s temporal
  regime.</p>
        <p>Our discussion falls into four main sections. In
  <xref alt="How to make time" rid="how-to-make-time-nb-article">How to make
  time</xref>, we present a theory of ‘temporal mapping’ to show how
  temporal regimes can be produced through repetition, representation
  and technicity. In
  <xref alt="Wikipedia time (1): the primacy of the past" rid="wikipedia-time-1-the-primacy-of-the-past-nb-article">Wikipedia
  time (1): the primacy of the past</xref>, we consider existing
  research into Wikipedia’s temporal regime, and consider the various
  ways that time enters into the encyclopaedia. In
  <xref alt="The birth of the bot that makes history" rid="the-birth-of-the-bot-that-makes-history-nb-article">The
  birth of the bot that makes history</xref>, we describe the series of
  events that led to Yapperbot/uncurrenter’s creation, and use a range
  of qualitative and quantitiative methods to analyse its contributions
  to Wikipedia. Finally, in
  <xref alt="Wikipedia time (2): encyclopaedia time" rid="wikipedia-time-2-encyclopaedia-time-nb-article">Wikipedia
  time (2): encyclopaedia time</xref>, we offer our conclusions about
  Wikipedia’s temporal regime, contextualising Wikipedia as one in a
  long line of encyclopaedic projects that attempt to encompass time. We
  conclude that Wikipedia’s temporal regime is <italic>complex regime of
  historicity</italic>. It is <italic>complex</italic> because it is a
  clash of many temporalities, which are contested by the people and
  other actors on the platform. It is <italic>historicist</italic>
  because it attempts to situate its human participants in the process
  of history through literary representation. The example of Wikipedia’s
  <italic>complex historicity</italic> supports the idea that time
  remains contingent. There is no fixed regime of digital time or
  network time. Time is out there for the making.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="how-to-make-time-nb-article">
        <title>How to make time</title>
        <p>We make temporal regimes by mixing time and space. We map time. The
  crying of the infant, the waxing of the moon, the rising of the dough,
  the coming of the moths, the shadow of the sundial, the alignment of
  the text, the stellar orientation of the standing stones—all are maps,
  which crystallise time in space. Whether this mapping occurs by
  analysis or synthesis depends on your view of time. For Henri Bergson,
  the ‘spatialization’ of time is analytic. Time is fundamentally
  <italic>duration</italic> [<italic>durée</italic>]. Our basic
  experience of time is continuous. When we spatialize time, we divide
  it, for instance when split it into hours and minutes, and map these
  divisions onto the clock
  (<xref alt="1984, 71–72" rid="ref-bergson_oeuvres_1984-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1984,
  71–72</xref>). For Arthur Schopenhauer, by contrast, the
  spatialization of time is synthetic. Our basic experience of time is
  discontinuous. Time is an endless series of unique moments:
  ‘Succession is the whole being of time’
  (<xref alt="Schopenhauer 1999, vol. 1" rid="ref-schopenhauer_werke_1999-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Schopenhauer
  1999, vol. 1</xref>, p. 37).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-nb-article">1</xref> We
  can only form a conception of the ‘duration’ [<italic>Dauer</italic>]
  of things when time and space are united in the ‘understanding’
  [<italic>Verstand</italic>]
  (<xref alt="1999, vol. 1" rid="ref-schopenhauer_werke_1999-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1999,
  vol. 1</xref>, p. 40). Had Schopenhauer experienced the cinema, he
  might have chosen it as his metaphor. From the whirring filmstrip of
  individual moments, we project the movie of life. Bergson rejected the
  cinema as a metaphor for consciousness
  (<xref alt="1984, 752ff" rid="ref-bergson_oeuvres_1984-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1984,
  752ff</xref>). For him, the Kantian view of time as succession
  insufficiently distinguishes time from space. To think time as
  succession, we need to use a spatial metaphor such as a ‘line’ or
  ‘chain’, and ‘juxtapose’ time’s moments along it
  (<xref alt="1984, 68" rid="ref-bergson_oeuvres_1984-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1984,
  68</xref>).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-nb-article">2</xref> A Kantian like
  Schopenhauer might reply that Bergson is too empirical. What makes it
  possible for Bergson to experience time as a non-spatial duration, if
  not the synthetic activity of the understanding?</p>
        <p>Whichever theory of spatialization we adopt, it is clear that there
  are many ways to map time. The time of the wheat is not the time of
  the Twitter feed. The sheer variety of temporal mappings is a key
  theme in the work of Mikhail Bakhtin. In his classic study of the
  ‘chronotope’, Bakhtin argues that different forms of literature are
  defined by their different forms of time
  (<xref alt="1981, 85" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  85</xref>). Greek romance is charactersised by ‘adventure-time’
  (<xref alt="1981, 87" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  87</xref>), modern fiction by ‘historical time’
  (<xref alt="1981, 165" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  165</xref>), Dostoyevsky’s existential novels by ‘mystery- and
  carnvial-time’
  (<xref alt="1981, 249" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  249</xref>). The time-mapping technology in this case is writing.
  Writers shape time with words. Words can shape time literally, for
  instance when Greek romanciers stitch together the moments of
  adventure-time using ‘link-words’ such as ‘suddenly’ or ‘at that
  moment’
  (<xref alt="1981, 92" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  92</xref>). Words can shape time symbolically, for instance when a
  writer portrays the ‘path of life’ as a road
  (<xref alt="1981, 120" rid="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1981,
  120</xref>). Bakhtin demonstrates how a technology such as writing can
  constitute different forms of time; indeed, his researches support the
  more radical argument of Bernard Stiegler, who claims that ‘organized
  inorganic beings’ such as novels might be generally
  ‘<italic>constitutive</italic> … of temporality as well as spatiality’
  (<xref alt="1998, 17" rid="ref-stiegler_technics_1998-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1998,
  17</xref>). We experience time and space through the maps we make of
  them.</p>
        <p>Maps structure time by structuring attention. The Sunderland
  petitioners in 1800: ‘many people are obliged to be up at all hours of
  the night to attend the tides’ (quoted in
  <xref alt="Thompson 1967, 60" rid="ref-thompson_time_1967-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Thompson
  1967, 60</xref>). To <italic>attend</italic>. The tides rise and fall
  (<italic>repetition</italic>). Through their height, they tell the the
  hour, day, month and season (<italic>representation</italic>). They
  are known partly by sight, and partly by moon-phase and tide-chart and
  plumb-line (<italic>technicity</italic>). To attend upon the tides is
  to know not only <italic>what</italic> time it is (high tide, spring),
  but <italic>what kind</italic> of time it is (to depart or return). In
  this way, attention plays a ‘constructive role … in fabricating tools
  and technical ensembles’
  (<xref alt="Hayles 2012, 91" rid="ref-hayles_how_2012-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Hayles
  2012, 91</xref>). The boat, the compass, the fishing-line and the
  fisher are fused together by attention on the tides.</p>
        <p>Through the power of attention, temporal <italic>maps</italic> can
  uphold temporal <italic>regimes</italic>. The classic example comes
  from the Industrial Revolution. Thompson
  (<xref alt="1967" rid="ref-thompson_time_1967-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1967</xref>)
  memorably describes the scene. As the ‘need for the synchronization of
  labour’ grew, so did the need for ‘[a]ttention to time’
  (<xref alt="Thompson 1967, 70" rid="ref-thompson_time_1967-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Thompson
  1967, 70</xref>)—or rather, the need for a particular kind of
  attention, which Thompson calls ‘time-discipline’. Masters used the
  factory clock (a map) to impose time-discipline on their workers (a
  regime). They fiddled with the clock to extract more hours of labour.
  They handed out gold watches for long service. Workers themselves
  would blow a windfall on a watch of their own—for the status, or the
  power? This example demonstrates why the repetition-theory of
  Orlikowski and Yates
  (<xref alt="2002" rid="ref-orlikowski_its_2002-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>)
  must be supplemented by the concepts of representation and technicity.
  The ‘recurrent action’ of factory workers can only be fully explained
  if we include the clock, which represented time as a succession of
  hours and minutes to be spent working, and which legitimated the new
  temporal regime by its (apparent) impersonality.</p>
        <p>Not all temporal maps are as strict or authoritative as Thompson’s
  factory-clock. Theorists of <italic>technicity</italic> observe that
  technical objects vary greatly in their degree of ‘concretization’
  (<xref alt="Stiegler 1998" rid="ref-stiegler_technics_1998-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Stiegler
  1998</xref>). Concretization is a process of unification. As a
  technology becomes more concrete, its parts become ‘organs’ that
  ‘function more and more as parts of a whole’
  (<xref alt="Stiegler 1998, 71" rid="ref-stiegler_technics_1998-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Stiegler
  1998, 71</xref>). It thus becomes autonomous. It ceases to be a
  ‘utensil’ of a human ‘actor’; it becomes itself an ‘actor’ with human
  ‘operators’
  (<xref alt="Stiegler 1998, 66" rid="ref-stiegler_technics_1998-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Stiegler
  1998, 66</xref>). The drying of hops was once regulated by the dryer,
  who touched and smelt the cones to determine the drying-time. The
  dryer relied on comparatively abstract technology (the oast-house and
  its cowl) to regulate the time by regulating the temperature and
  humidity. Today, the dryer is a machine, which determines the
  drying-time autonomously using clocks and sensors. Such a concrete
  technology in effect concretizes time itself. The drying-time is
  nothing but the time it takes for the machine to work.</p>
        <p>In the same way we characterise technicities as
  <italic>concrete</italic> or <italic>abstract</italic>, we can
  characterise repetitions as <italic>regular</italic> or
  <italic>irregular</italic>, and representations as
  <italic>clear</italic> or <italic>vague</italic>. Thompson
  (<xref alt="1967" rid="ref-thompson_time_1967-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1967</xref>)
  repeatedly stresses the ‘regularity’ of capitalist work-patterns, as
  opposed to the ‘irregularity’ of work in pre-capitalist temporal
  regimes. While we may reject Thompson’s schematism, we must accept his
  observation that repetition can vary in its lawfulness and
  predictability. The tanpura drones regularly while the sitar wanders
  in endless novelty. In much the same way, a representation of time can
  be clear and bright or vague and suggestive. A modern composer gives
  the tempo in beats per minute, where a Romantic requests the orchestra
  to play <italic>Bewegt, doch nicht schnell</italic>.</p>
        <p>Temporal regimes are seldom unitary. They combine many temporal
  maps to create a ‘multiplicity’
  (<xref alt="Orlikowski and Yates 2002, 687" rid="ref-orlikowski_its_2002-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Orlikowski
  and Yates 2002, 687</xref>) or ‘complex’ of temporalities
  (<xref alt="Hayles 2012, 89" rid="ref-hayles_how_2012-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Hayles
  2012, 89</xref>). This complexity is especially apparent on the plane
  of representation. Digital media can present many different interfaces
  to time. A Wikipedia article represents time as a connected narrative
  on the ‘Article’ tab, as a list of versions on the ‘View history’ tab,
  as an ongoing debate between editors on the ‘Talk’ tab, as a
  time-series of web hits on the Pageviews tool, as a pie-chart of
  contributions on the XTools interface, as an immutable series of
  transactions in the underlying MYSQL database, and so on. Such
  interfaces form a single unstable ‘complex’ because they are folded
  together by Wikipedia’s various actors. This complexity leads to
  contradiction, which leads to contention, which led, in one case, to
  Yapperbot/uncurrenter.</p>
        <p>In sum, we define a temporal regime as a system of temporal maps
  that structure a particular form of life through the modulation of
  human attention. We can now refine our research questions. How do
  Wikipedians map time? Which mappings are established, which are
  contested, and how does Yapperbot/uncurrenter fit among them? How has
  digital technology changed the nature of temporal mapping?</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="wikipedia-time-1-the-primacy-of-the-past-nb-article">
        <title>Wikipedia time (1): the primacy of the past</title>
        <p>
          <italic>TODO: Rewrite/adapt</italic>
        </p>
        <p>How does Wikipedia portray the past? Scholars typically give three
  answers. Some argue that Wikipedia produces <italic>history</italic>:
  it represents the past in literary form. Wikipedia history may be more
  “colorful,” “anecdotal” and “factualist” than “professional history,”
  observes Roy Rosenzweig, but history it most certainly is
  (<xref alt="Rosenzweig 2006, 142" rid="ref-rosenzweig_can_2006-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Rosenzweig
  2006, 142</xref>). Others argue that Wikipedia articles comprise
  <italic>collective memories</italic> that evoke shared experiences.
  From this perspective, Wikipedia’s Talk pages are more important than
  the articles themselves, and its editors are more important than its
  readers. As Christian Pentzold argues, Wikipedia’s Talk pages are
  non-physical “memory places,” where editors meet to “negotiat[e]” the
  “memorable elements” of their experiences
  (<xref alt="Pentzold 2009, 264" rid="ref-pentzold_fixing_2009-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Pentzold
  2009, 264</xref>). Numerous scholars have followed in Pentzold’s wake
  to examine how editors “build” or “form” collective memories in
  Wikipedia
  (<xref alt="Ferron and Massa 2011b" rid="ref-ferron_collective_2011-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Ferron
  and Massa 2011b</xref>,
  <xref alt="2011a" rid="ref-ferron_arab_2011-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2011a</xref>;
  <xref alt="Porter, Krafft, and Keegan 2020" rid="ref-porter_visual_2020-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Porter,
  Krafft, and Keegan 2020</xref>). A third group of scholars argue that
  Wikipedia is a repository of <italic>facts</italic>. Wikipedia may
  well publish works of history and store collective memories, but its
  main role is to produce atomistic facts that are propagated through
  knowledge graphs
  (<xref alt="Ford 2020" rid="ref-ford_rise_2020-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Ford
  2020</xref>,
  <xref alt="2022" rid="ref-ford_writing_2022-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2022</xref>).
  Wikipedia may be <italic>memory</italic> to thousands of editors. It
  may be <italic>history</italic> to millions of readers. But it is mere
  <italic>fact</italic> to billions of search requests and API
  calls.</p>
        <p>These approaches are not mutually exclusive. Search engines,
  readers and editors all produce and consume Wikipedia in different
  ways, and a complete account of the encyclopedia must include them
  all. In which case, we must ask: how are the historical, memorial and
  factual aspects of Wikipedia related?</p>
        <p>One way to approach this question is to focus precisely on the
  <italic>pastness</italic> of history, memory and fact. Pastness is
  central to Wikipedia’s self-definition. “Wikipedia is not a crystal
  ball,” reads
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WP:NOT">a
  famous policy</ext-link>, wherein we also read that Wikipedia is “not
  a newspaper.” It is the pastness of Wikipedia that allows it to
  function simultaneously as history, memory and fact. Pastness is
  obviously a feature of both history and memory: I cannot remember an
  event nor write its history until it has happened. The pastness of
  <italic>fact</italic> is less obvious. Wikipedia contains facts about
  fictional spacecraft, embroidery techniques and the heat death of the
  universe. In what sense can such facts be said to be “past”?</p>
        <p>Wikipedia itself provides an answer in two of its foundational
  policies. According to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:No_original_research">‘No
  Original Research’</ext-link>, no new facts are to be admitted to the
  encyclopaedia. The only allowable facts are—the <italic>old</italic>.
  According to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Neutral_point_of_view">‘Neutral
  Point of View’</ext-link>, no controversial facts are to be admitted
  to the encyclopaedia. The only allowable facts are—the
  <italic>settled</italic>. Facts are geological. Only time can grind
  down the seashells of evidence and bring forth the limestone of
  objectivity. Editors who wish to include new or unsettled facts in the
  encyclopaedia are advised that
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:There_is_no_deadline">‘There
  is no deadline’</ext-link>. <italic>Þæs oferēode; þisses swa
  mæg.</italic> That passed; so may this. Eventually everything is
  past.</p>
        <p>Despite its supposed pastness, Wikipedia is well-known as a source
  of information on current events. It is ‘An Encylopedia with Breaking
  News’
  (<xref alt="Keegan 2019" rid="ref-keegan_encyclopedia_2019-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Keegan
  2019</xref>). Current events dominate Wikipedia, accounting for the
  lion’s share of user contributions and page views at any given time
  (<xref alt="Keegan, Gergle, and Contractor 2011" rid="ref-keegan_hot_2011-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Keegan,
  Gergle, and Contractor 2011</xref>). Scholars have analysed
  Wikipedia’s coverage of current events in detail. We now know how
  Wikipedia’s editors clash over the nature and definition of current
  events
  (<xref alt="Ford 2022" rid="ref-ford_writing_2022-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Ford
  2022</xref>;
  <xref alt="Pentzold 2009" rid="ref-pentzold_fixing_2009-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Pentzold
  2009</xref>), how they link current events into larger thematic
  structures
  (<xref alt="Twyman, Keegan, and Shaw 2017" rid="ref-twyman_black_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Twyman,
  Keegan, and Shaw 2017</xref>), how they adopt newsroom practices to
  co-ordinate their efforts
  (<xref alt="Avieson 2019" rid="ref-avieson_breaking_2019-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Avieson
  2019</xref>), how they revisit old articles to commemorate traumatic
  events
  (<xref alt="Ferron and Massa 2014" rid="ref-ferron_beyond_2014-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Ferron
  and Massa 2014</xref>), and how they shape the interpretation of
  events using images
  (<xref alt="Porter, Krafft, and Keegan 2020" rid="ref-porter_visual_2020-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Porter,
  Krafft, and Keegan 2020</xref>). One thing we <italic>don’t</italic>
  know is how Wikipedia’s editors decide what is ‘current’. How does
  Wikipedia distinguish the past from the present at the very threshold
  of time? How does it resolve the contradiction between the pastness of
  the encyclopaedia and the presentness of the current?</p>
        <p>Most readers of Wikipedia will have seen what editors do when an
  article trespasses on the present: mark it with one of the available
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Current_event_templates">Current
  Event Templates</ext-link>. The main template is
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Current">Template:Current</ext-link>,
  which at the time of writing is available on 116 language editions of
  Wikipedia. When the template is added to an article, a familiar banner
  appears at the top of the page (Figure ), and the article is
  automatically added to
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Current_events">Category:Current
  Events</ext-link> or a related category. Each language edition has its
  own distinct version of Template:Current, and may also sport a range
  of related Templates. French Wikipedia, for instance, distinguishes
  ‘Événements en cours’ [ongoing events] from ‘Événements récents’
  [recent events] in its
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mod%C3%A8le:%C3%89v%C3%A9nement_en_cours">main
  template</ext-link>, and provides several related templates such as
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mod%C3%A8le:Bataille_en_cours">Modèle:Bataille
  en cours</ext-link> [Template:Ongoing battle] and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mod%C3%A8le:Mort_r%C3%A9cente">Modèle:Mort
  récente</ext-link> [Template:Recent death]. German Wikipedia, by
  contrast, has only a single
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vorlage:Laufendes_Ereignis">Current
  Events template</ext-link>, but it is customisable, so that editors
  can replace the phrase “aktuelles Ereignis” [current event] in the
  banner with a more specific description such as “die derzeitige
  Sportveranstaltung” [the ongoing sporting event].</p>
        <p>New twist in the tale: a user ‘killed’ Yapperbot/uncurrent on
  24/4/2023 because
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=1151461527&amp;oldid=986550108&amp;title=User%3AYapperbot%2Fkill%2FUncurrenter">they
  complained it had removed {{current}} from a current
  event</ext-link>.</p>
        <p>On the surface, Template:Current might seem like a simple
  phenomenon. Editors mark an article when it is “current,” then remove
  the template when its currency is ended. Avieson
  (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-avieson_breaking_2019-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)
  likens Template:Current to the “live” icon on a newspaper blog or
  television news. While Template:Current is present, the article
  functions as live coverage; when the template is removed, the article
  gradually becomes encyclopaedic.</p>
        <p>But the use of Template:Current is not simple, and has vexed
  Wikipedia’s editors for years. Avieson
  (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-avieson_breaking_2019-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)
  herself grapples with the problem. Although she argues for a
  distinction between “news” and “encyclopaedias,” she also observes
  that Wikipedia’s coverage of current events “blurs the boundaries of
  both news and temporality.” These blurred boundaries are a problem for
  Wikipedia’s editors, and editors in different langauges have clarified
  the distinction between past, present and future in different ways. In
  this context, English Wikipedia is extremist. Unlike other language
  editions, English Wikipedia strictly polices the use of
  Template:Current with a bot:
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Yapperbot">Yapperbot/uncurrenter</ext-link>.
  Yapperbot/uncurrenter scans English Wikipedia hourly, examining every
  article that includes Template:Current and deleting the template if
  the article has not been edited in the last five hours. English
  Wikipedia is also one of the few larger language editions without a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Future">Template:Future</ext-link>
  to mark events that have yet to occur. English Wikipedia deleted
  Template:Future in 2009 after an official process, and several
  attempts to resurrect the template have foundered. Meanwhile French,
  Italian, Bengali, Chinese and 51 other-language Wikipedias maintain a
  Template:Future.</p>
        <p>Why does practice vary across the different language editions? What
  led to the extremely strict approach of English Wikipedia, in which
  Template:Current is ruthlessly policed by an artificial agent, and the
  future is not explicitly marked? What can this tell us about
  Wikipedia’s “temporal regime”
  (<xref alt="Assmann 2020" rid="ref-assmann_is_2020-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Assmann
  2020</xref>)?</p>
        <p>We try to answer these questions by focussing on
  Yapperbot/uncurrenter. We describe the history of Template:Current and
  recount the debates that led to the bot’s creation. We then examine
  Yapperbot/uncurrenter’s contributions to English Wikipedia, comparing
  its practice with the practice of human editors on English Wikipedia
  and other-language Wikipedias.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="the-birth-of-the-bot-that-makes-history-nb-article">
        <title>The birth of the bot that makes history</title>
        <list list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Qualitative methods:</italic> Reading the talk pages,
      bot approval etc. that led to the creation of
      Yapperbot/uncurrenter</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Quantitative methods:</italic> Comparison of
      Yapperbot/uncurrenter with humans who have policed
      Template:Current using wikkitidy
      (<xref alt="Falk 2023" rid="ref-falk_wikkitidy_2023-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Falk
      2023</xref>) and the tidyverse
      (<xref alt="Wickham et al. 2019" rid="ref-wickham_welcome_2019-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Wickham
      et al. 2019</xref>).</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Methodology:</italic> Trace ethnography
      (<xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger and Ribes 2011" rid="ref-geiger_trace_2011-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">R.
      Stuart Geiger and Ribes 2011</xref>); ethnography of algorithmic
      systems
      (<xref alt="Seaver 2017" rid="ref-seaver_algorithms_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">Seaver
      2017</xref>;
      <xref alt="R. Stuart Geiger 2017" rid="ref-geiger_beyond_2017-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">R.
      Stuart Geiger 2017</xref>).</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <sec id="nb-code-cell-3-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-code">
          <code language="r script">get_yapperbot &lt;- function(data_dir = "data", use_cache = FALSE) {
  data_files &lt;- list.files(data_dir)
  yp_files = stringr::str_detect(data_files, "yapperbot-contribs-to")
  if (!any(yp_files) | !use_cache) {
    # Download all yapperbot's contributions
    yapperbot &lt;- wikkitidy::wiki_action_request() %&gt;%
      wikkitidy::get_list_of(
        "usercontribs",
        ucuser = "Yapperbot",
        uclimit = "max",
        ucprop = "comment|ids|title|timestamp",
        ucnamespace = 0
      ) %&gt;%
      wikkitidy::retrieve_all() %&gt;% 
      filter(stringr::str_detect(comment, "current"))
    write_csv(
      yapperbot,
      file.path(
        data_dir,
        glue::glue("yapperbot-contribs-to-{as.integer(Sys.time())}.csv")
        )
    )
  } else {
    latest_file &lt;- sort(data_files[yp_files], decreasing = TRUE)[1]
    yapperbot &lt;- read_csv(file = file.path(data_dir, latest_file))
  }
  # Final transformations before import into document
  yapperbot %&gt;%
    mutate(timestamp = lubridate::as_datetime(timestamp),
           date = lubridate::as_date(timestamp))
}

yapperbot &lt;- get_yapperbot(use_cache = T)</code>
          <sec id="nb-code-cell-3-output-0-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-output">
            <preformat>Rows: 1648 Columns: 10
── Column specification ────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
Delimiter: ","
chr  (3): user, title, comment
dbl  (5): userid, pageid, revid, parentid, ns
lgl  (1): texthidden
dttm (1): timestamp

ℹ Use `spec()` to retrieve the full column specification for this data.
ℹ Specify the column types or set `show_col_types = FALSE` to quiet this message.</preformat>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <p>
          <italic>How did `Yapperbot/uncurrenter’ come about? What were the
  debates and discussions of the editors? What was the perceived problem
  the bot was supposed to fix?</italic>
        </p>
        <p>
          <italic>What does the bot actually do? How does that compare with
  what it is supposed to do?</italic>
        </p>
        <p>How many pages is yapperbot uncurrenting per day?</p>
        <sec id="nb-code-cell-4-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-code">
          <code language="r script">yapperbot %&gt;%
  ggplot(aes(date)) +
  geom_bar() +
  labs(
    title = "Yapperbot usually uncurrents less than five articles a day",
    x = "Day",
    y = "Deletions of Template:Current"
  )</code>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="the-bot-that-makes-history_files/figure-jats/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png"/>
        </sec>
        <p>What was happening on that day it uncurrented 45 pages?</p>
        <sec id="nb-code-cell-5-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-code">
          <code language="r script">most_active_day &lt;- yapperbot %&gt;% 
  group_by(date) %&gt;% 
  summarise(count = n()) %&gt;% 
  slice_max(count, n=1)

yapperbot %&gt;% 
  filter(date == most_active_day$date) %&gt;% 
  select(pageid, title, timestamp)</code>
          <sec id="nb-code-cell-5-output-0-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-output">
            <preformat># A tibble: 45 × 3
     pageid title                                            timestamp          
      &lt;dbl&gt; &lt;chr&gt;                                            &lt;dttm&gt;             
 1 63362621 COVID-19 pandemic in Ethiopia                    2020-10-21 23:00:28
 2 63431783 COVID-19 pandemic in Northern Ireland            2020-10-21 22:00:48
 3 63181042 COVID-19 pandemic in Europe                      2020-10-21 22:00:41
 4 63178596 COVID-19 pandemic in Hong Kong                   2020-10-21 22:00:38
 5 63313047 COVID-19 pandemic in Moldova                     2020-10-21 21:00:43
 6 63239190 COVID-19 pandemic in Sweden                      2020-10-21 21:00:37
 7 64307024 Timeline of the COVID-19 pandemic in October 20… 2020-10-21 20:00:49
 8 63395521 COVID-19 pandemic in Sarawak                     2020-10-21 20:00:45
 9 63391509 COVID-19 pandemic in Quebec                      2020-10-21 20:00:39
10 63389195 COVID-19 pandemic in Sabah                       2020-10-21 20:00:36
# ℹ 35 more rows</preformat>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <p>How often does Yapperbot have to remove the template more than
  once?</p>
        <sec id="nb-code-cell-6-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-code">
          <code language="r script">yapperbot %&gt;% 
  group_by(pageid) %&gt;% 
  summarise(count = n()) %&gt;% 
  group_by(count) %&gt;% 
  summarise(num_pages = n())</code>
          <sec id="nb-code-cell-6-output-0-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-output">
            <preformat># A tibble: 7 × 2
  count num_pages
  &lt;int&gt;     &lt;int&gt;
1     1      1236
2     2       133
3     3        23
4     4         9
5     5         4
6     6         2
7     9         1</preformat>
          </sec>
        </sec>
        <p>Which page had to be uncurrented nine times?</p>
        <sec id="nb-code-cell-7-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-code">
          <code language="r script">yapperbot %&gt;% 
  group_by(pageid, title) %&gt;% 
  summarise(count = n()) %&gt;% 
  filter(count &gt; 4) %&gt;% 
  arrange(desc(count))</code>
          <sec id="nb-code-cell-7-output-0-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-output">
            <preformat>`summarise()` has grouped output by 'pageid'. You can override using the
`.groups` argument.</preformat>
          </sec>
          <sec id="nb-code-cell-7-output-1-nb-article" specific-use="notebook-output">
            <preformat># A tibble: 7 × 3
# Groups:   pageid [7]
    pageid title                                            count
     &lt;dbl&gt; &lt;chr&gt;                                            &lt;int&gt;
1 70168267 Siege of Mariupol                                    9
2 65760352 Tigray War                                           6
3 70161957 Siege of Chernihiv                                   6
4 64399515 2020–2021 Belarusian protests                        5
5 70157964 Timeline of the 2022 Russian invasion of Ukraine     5
6 70160923 Battle of Kharkiv (2022)                             5
7 70809573 2022–2023 monkeypox outbreak                         5</preformat>
          </sec>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="wikipedia-time-2-encyclopaedia-time-nb-article">
        <title>Wikipedia time (2): encyclopaedia time</title>
        <p>
          <italic>Compared to other temporal regimes</italic>
        </p>
      </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
      <ref-list>
        <title/>
        <ref id="ref-porter_visual_2020-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Porter</surname>
                <given-names>Emily</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Krafft</surname>
                <given-names>P. M.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Keegan</surname>
                <given-names>Brian</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Visual Narratives and Collective Memory across Peer-Produced Accounts of Contested Sociopolitical Events</article-title>
            <source>ACM Transactions on Social Computing</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2020-02">2020</year>
            <month>02</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-09">2023</year>
              <month>01</month>
              <day>09</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <volume>3</volume>
            <issue>1</issue>
            <issn>2469-7818</issn>
            <uri>http://doi.org/10.1145/3373147</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/3373147</pub-id>
            <fpage>4:1</fpage>
            <lpage>4:20</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-twyman_black_2017-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Twyman</surname>
                <given-names>Marlon</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Keegan</surname>
                <given-names>Brian C.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Shaw</surname>
                <given-names>Aaron</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Black Lives Matter in Wikipedia: Collaboration and Collective Memory around Online Social Movements</article-title>
            <source>Proceedings of the 2017 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2017-02">2017</year>
            <month>02</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-03">2023</year>
              <month>01</month>
              <day>03</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <uri>http://arxiv.org/abs/1611.01257</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2998181.2998232</pub-id>
            <fpage>1400</fpage>
            <lpage>1412</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-pentzold_fixing_2009-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Pentzold</surname>
                <given-names>Christian</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Fixing the floating gap: The online encyclopaedia Wikipedia as a global memory place</article-title>
            <source>Memory Studies</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2009-05">2009</year>
            <month>05</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-03">2023</year>
              <month>01</month>
              <day>03</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <volume>2</volume>
            <issue>2</issue>
            <issn>1750-6980, 1750-6999</issn>
            <uri>http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1750698008102055</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1750698008102055</pub-id>
            <fpage>255</fpage>
            <lpage>272</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-castells_rise_2010-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Castells</surname>
                <given-names>Manuel</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>The rise of the network society</source>
            <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Chichester, West Sussex ; Malden, MA</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
            <edition>2nd ed., with a new pref</edition>
            <isbn>978-1-4051-9686-4</isbn>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-ford_writing_2022-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Ford</surname>
                <given-names>Heather</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>Writing the revolution: Wikipedia and the survival of facts in the digital age</source>
            <publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year>
            <isbn>978-0-262-04629-9</isbn>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-rosenzweig_can_2006-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Rosenzweig</surname>
                <given-names>Roy</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Can History Be Open Source? Wikipedia and the Future of the Past</article-title>
            <source>The Journal of American History</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-23">2023</year>
              <month>01</month>
              <day>23</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <volume>93</volume>
            <issue>1</issue>
            <issn>0021-8723</issn>
            <uri>http://www.jstor.org/stable/4486062</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/4486062</pub-id>
            <fpage>117</fpage>
            <lpage>146</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-tkacz_wikipedia_2015-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Tkacz</surname>
                <given-names>Nathaniel</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>Wikipedia and the politics of openness</source>
            <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Chicago ; London</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
            <isbn>978-0-226-19227-7 978-0-226-19230-7</isbn>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-wajcman_pressed_2015-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Wajcman</surname>
                <given-names>Judy</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>Pressed for time: The acceleration of life in digital capitalism</source>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year>
            <isbn>978-0-226-19650-3</isbn>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7208/9780226196503</pub-id>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-keegan_encyclopedia_2019-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Keegan</surname>
                <given-names>Brian</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>An encyclopedia with breaking news</article-title>
            <source>Wikipedia@ 20: Stories of an Incomplete Revolution</source>
            <person-group person-group-type="editor">
              <name>
                <surname>Reagle</surname>
                <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Koerner</surname>
                <given-names>Jackie</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Mass</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year>
            <uri>https://doi.org/10.7551/mitpress/12366.003.0007</uri>
            <fpage>55</fpage>
            <lpage>70</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-avieson_breaking_2019-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Avieson</surname>
                <given-names>Bunty</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Breaking news on Wikipedia: Collaborating, collating and competing</article-title>
            <source>First Monday</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2019-04">2019</year>
            <month>04</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-30">2023</year>
              <month>01</month>
              <day>30</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <issn>1396-0466</issn>
            <uri>https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/9530</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5210/fm.v24i5.9530</pub-id>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-keegan_hot_2011-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Keegan</surname>
                <given-names>Brian</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Gergle</surname>
                <given-names>Darren</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Contractor</surname>
                <given-names>Noshir</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Hot off the wiki: Dynamics, practices, and structures in Wikipedia’s coverage of the Tōhoku catastrophes</article-title>
            <source>Proceedings of the 7th International Symposium on Wikis and Open Collaboration</source>
            <publisher-name>ACM</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Mountain View California</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2011-10">2011</year>
            <month>10</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-30">2023</year>
              <month>01</month>
              <day>30</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <isbn>978-1-4503-0909-7</isbn>
            <uri>https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/2038558.2038577</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2038558.2038577</pub-id>
            <fpage>105</fpage>
            <lpage>113</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-ferron_arab_2011-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Ferron</surname>
                <given-names>Michela</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Massa</surname>
                <given-names>Paolo</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>The Arab Spring wikirevolutions: Wikipedia as a lens for studying the real-time formation of collective memories of revolutions</article-title>
            <source>International Journal of Communication</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
            <volume>5</volume>
            <fpage>20</fpage>
            <lpage/>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-ferron_beyond_2014-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Ferron</surname>
                <given-names>Michela</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Massa</surname>
                <given-names>Paolo</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Beyond the encyclopedia: Collective memories in Wikipedia</article-title>
            <source>Memory Studies</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
            <volume>7</volume>
            <issue>1</issue>
            <fpage>22</fpage>
            <lpage>45</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-gumbrecht_our_2014-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Gumbrecht</surname>
                <given-names>Hans Ulrich</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>Our broad present: Time and contemporary culture</source>
            <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
            <isbn>978-0-231-16360-6 978-0-231-16361-3</isbn>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-ferron_collective_2011-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Ferron</surname>
                <given-names>Michela</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Massa</surname>
                <given-names>Paolo</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Collective memory building in Wikipedia: The case of North African uprisings</article-title>
            <source>Proceedings of the 7th International Symposium on Wikis and Open Collaboration</source>
            <publisher-name>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2011-10">2011</year>
            <month>10</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-26">2023</year>
              <month>02</month>
              <day>26</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <isbn>978-1-4503-0909-7</isbn>
            <uri>https://doi.org/10.1145/2038558.2038578</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2038558.2038578</pub-id>
            <fpage>114</fpage>
            <lpage>123</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-ford_rise_2020-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Ford</surname>
                <given-names>Heather</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Rise of the Underdog</article-title>
            <source>Wikipedia@20: Stories of an Incomplete Revolution</source>
            <person-group person-group-type="editor">
              <name>
                <surname>Reagle</surname>
                <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Koerner</surname>
                <given-names>Jackie</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Mass</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2020-10">2020</year>
            <month>10</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-27">2023</year>
              <month>02</month>
              <day>27</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <uri>https://direct.mit.edu/books/book/4956/chapter/1879827/Rise-of-the-Underdog</uri>
            <fpage>189</fpage>
            <lpage>201</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-assmann_is_2020-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Assmann</surname>
                <given-names>Aleida</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>Is Time out of Joint?: On the Rise and Fall of the Modern Time Regime</source>
            <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Ithaca, UNITED STATES</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-01-26">2023</year>
              <month>01</month>
              <day>26</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <isbn>978-1-5017-4245-3</isbn>
            <uri>http://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/uts/detail.action?docID=5964894</uri>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-geiger_when_2013-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Geiger</surname>
                <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Halfaker</surname>
                <given-names>Aaron</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>When the levee breaks: Without bots, what happens to Wikipedia’s quality control processes?</article-title>
            <source>Proceedings of the 9th International Symposium on Open Collaboration</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>6</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-geiger_work_2010-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Geiger</surname>
                <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ribes</surname>
                <given-names>David</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>The work of sustaining order in Wikipedia: The banning of a vandal</article-title>
            <source>Proceedings of the 2010 ACM conference on Computer supported cooperative work</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
            <fpage>117</fpage>
            <lpage>126</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-geiger_are_2013-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Geiger</surname>
                <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Are computers merely" supporting" cooperative work: Towards an ethnography of bot development</article-title>
            <source>Proceedings of the 2013 conference on Computer supported cooperative work companion</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
            <fpage>51</fpage>
            <lpage>56</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-geiger_social_2009-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Geiger</surname>
                <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>The social roles of bots and assisted editing programs</article-title>
            <source>Proceedings of the 5th International Symposium on Wikis and Open Collaboration</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>2</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-geiger_lives_2011-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Geiger</surname>
                <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>The lives of bots</article-title>
            <source>Critical Point of View: A Wikipedia Reader</source>
            <person-group person-group-type="editor">
              <name>
                <surname>Lovink</surname>
                <given-names>Geert</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Tkacz</surname>
                <given-names>Nathaniel</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <publisher-name>Amsterdam</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Institute of Network Cultures</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
            <fpage>78</fpage>
            <lpage>93</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-geiger_operationalizing_2017-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Geiger</surname>
                <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Halfaker</surname>
                <given-names>Aaron</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Operationalizing conflict and cooperation between automated software agents in wikipedia: A replication and expansion of’even good bots fight’</article-title>
            <source>Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
            <volume>1</volume>
            <issue>CSCW</issue>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>33</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-geiger_beyond_2017-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Geiger</surname>
                <given-names>R Stuart</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Beyond opening up the black box: Investigating the role of algorithmic systems in Wikipedian organizational culture</article-title>
            <source>Big Data &amp; Society</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2017-12">2017</year>
            <month>12</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-28">2023</year>
              <month>02</month>
              <day>28</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <volume>4</volume>
            <issue>2</issue>
            <issn>2053-9517, 2053-9517</issn>
            <uri>http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/2053951717730735</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2053951717730735</pub-id>
            <fpage>205395171773073</fpage>
            <lpage/>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-niederer_wisdom_2010-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Niederer</surname>
                <given-names>Sabine</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Dijck</surname>
                <given-names>José van</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Wisdom of the crowd or technicity of content? Wikipedia as a sociotechnical system</article-title>
            <source>New Media &amp; Society</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2010-12">2010</year>
            <month>12</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-28">2023</year>
              <month>02</month>
              <day>28</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <volume>12</volume>
            <issue>8</issue>
            <issn>1461-4448</issn>
            <uri>https://doi.org/10.1177/1461444810365297</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1461444810365297</pub-id>
            <fpage>1368</fpage>
            <lpage>1387</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-halfaker_bots_2012-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Halfaker</surname>
                <given-names>Aaron</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Riedl</surname>
                <given-names>John</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Bots and Cyborgs: Wikipedia’s Immune System</article-title>
            <source>Computer</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2012-03">2012</year>
            <month>03</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-28">2023</year>
              <month>02</month>
              <day>28</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <volume>45</volume>
            <issue>3</issue>
            <issn>0018-9162</issn>
            <uri>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/6163451/</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/MC.2012.82</pub-id>
            <fpage>79</fpage>
            <lpage>82</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-seaver_algorithms_2017-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Seaver</surname>
                <given-names>Nick</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Algorithms as culture: Some tactics for the ethnography of algorithmic systems</article-title>
            <source>Big data &amp; society</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
            <volume>4</volume>
            <issue>2</issue>
            <fpage>2053951717738104</fpage>
            <lpage/>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-dijck_culture_2013-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Dijck</surname>
                <given-names>José van</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>The culture of connectivity: A critical history of social media</source>
            <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Oxford ; New York</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
            <isbn>978-0-19-997077-3 978-0-19-997078-0</isbn>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-kennedy_textual_2010-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Kennedy</surname>
                <given-names>Krista</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Textual Machinery: Authorial Agency and Bot-Written Texts in Wikipedia</article-title>
            <source>The Responsibilities of Rhetoric</source>
            <person-group person-group-type="editor">
              <name>
                <surname>Smith</surname>
                <given-names>Michelle</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Warnick</surname>
                <given-names>Barbara</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <publisher-name>Waveland</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Long Grove, Illinois</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
            <uri>https://surface.syr.edu/wp/1</uri>
            <fpage>303</fpage>
            <lpage>309</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-livingstone_population_2016-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Livingstone</surname>
                <given-names>Randall M.</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Population automation: An interview with Wikipedia bot pioneer Ram-Man</article-title>
            <source>First Monday</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2016-01">2016</year>
            <month>01</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-02-28">2023</year>
              <month>02</month>
              <day>28</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <issn>1396-0466</issn>
            <uri>https://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/6027</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5210/fm.v21i1.6027</pub-id>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-hartog_regimes_2017-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Hartog</surname>
                <given-names>François</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>Regimes of historicity: Presentism and experiences of time</source>
            <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year>
            <edition>Paperback edition</edition>
            <isbn>978-0-231-16377-4</isbn>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-geiger_trace_2011-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="paper-conference">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Geiger</surname>
                <given-names>R. Stuart</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ribes</surname>
                <given-names>David</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Trace Ethnography: Following Coordination through Documentary Practices</article-title>
            <source>2011 44th Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2011-01">2011</year>
            <month>01</month>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/HICSS.2011.455</pub-id>
            <fpage>1</fpage>
            <lpage>10</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-wickham_welcome_2019-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Wickham</surname>
                <given-names>Hadley</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Averick</surname>
                <given-names>Mara</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Bryan</surname>
                <given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Chang</surname>
                <given-names>Winston</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>McGowan</surname>
                <given-names>Lucy D’Agostino</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>François</surname>
                <given-names>Romain</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Grolemund</surname>
                <given-names>Garrett</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Hayes</surname>
                <given-names>Alex</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Henry</surname>
                <given-names>Lionel</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Hester</surname>
                <given-names>Jim</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Kuhn</surname>
                <given-names>Max</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Pedersen</surname>
                <given-names>Thomas Lin</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Miller</surname>
                <given-names>Evan</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Bache</surname>
                <given-names>Stephan Milton</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Müller</surname>
                <given-names>Kirill</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Ooms</surname>
                <given-names>Jeroen</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Robinson</surname>
                <given-names>David</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Seidel</surname>
                <given-names>Dana Paige</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Spinu</surname>
                <given-names>Vitalie</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Takahashi</surname>
                <given-names>Kohske</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Vaughan</surname>
                <given-names>Davis</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Wilke</surname>
                <given-names>Claus</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Woo</surname>
                <given-names>Kara</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Yutani</surname>
                <given-names>Hiroaki</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Welcome to the Tidyverse</article-title>
            <source>Journal of Open Source Software</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2019-11">2019</year>
            <month>11</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-03-27">2023</year>
              <month>03</month>
              <day>27</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <volume>4</volume>
            <issue>43</issue>
            <issn>2475-9066</issn>
            <uri>https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.01686</uri>
            <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01686</pub-id>
            <fpage>1686</fpage>
            <lpage/>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-falk_wikkitidy_2023-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Falk</surname>
                <given-names>Michael</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>Wikkitidy: Tidy analysis of Wikipedia in R</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2023">2023</year>
            <uri>https://wikihistories.github.io/wikkitidy/</uri>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-orlikowski_its_2002-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Orlikowski</surname>
                <given-names>Wanda J.</given-names>
              </name>
              <name>
                <surname>Yates</surname>
                <given-names>JoAnne</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>It’s about time: Temporal structuring in organizations</article-title>
            <source>Organization Science</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="2002-12">2002</year>
            <month>12</month>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-03-28">2023</year>
              <month>03</month>
              <day>28</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <volume>13</volume>
            <issue>6</issue>
            <issn>10477039</issn>
            <uri>https://www.proquest.com/docview/213829873/abstract/57070C934917444CPQ/1</uri>
            <fpage>684</fpage>
            <lpage>700</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-thompson_time_1967-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Thompson</surname>
                <given-names>E. P.</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <article-title>Time, Work-Discipline, and Industrial Capitalism</article-title>
            <source>Past &amp; Present</source>
            <year iso-8601-date="1967">1967</year>
            <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
              <year iso-8601-date="2023-03-31">2023</year>
              <month>03</month>
              <day>31</day>
            </date-in-citation>
            <issue>38</issue>
            <issn>0031-2746</issn>
            <uri>https://www.jstor.org/stable/649749</uri>
            <fpage>56</fpage>
            <lpage>97</lpage>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-bergson_oeuvres_1984-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Bergson</surname>
                <given-names>Henri</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>Œuvres</source>
            <person-group person-group-type="editor">
              <name>
                <surname>Robinet</surname>
                <given-names>André</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <publisher-name>Presses universitaires de France</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="1984">1984</year>
            <edition>4e</edition>
            <isbn>978-2-13-038495-3</isbn>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-bakhtin_dialogic_1981-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Bakhtin</surname>
                <given-names>Mikhail</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>The Dialogic Imagination: Four Essays</source>
            <person-group person-group-type="editor">
              <name>
                <surname>Holquist</surname>
                <given-names>Michael</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <publisher-name>University of Texas Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="1981">1981</year>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-stiegler_technics_1998-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Stiegler</surname>
                <given-names>Bernard</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>Technics and time</source>
            <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Stanford, Calif</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year>
            <isbn>978-0-8047-3040-2 978-0-8047-3041-9 978-0-8047-3012-9</isbn>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-schopenhauer_werke_1999-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Schopenhauer</surname>
                <given-names>Arthur</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>Werke in 5 Bänden mit einem Beibuch</source>
            <person-group person-group-type="editor">
              <name>
                <surname>Lütkehaus</surname>
                <given-names>Ludger</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <publisher-name>Haffmans Verlag</publisher-name>
            <year iso-8601-date="1999">1999</year>
            <edition>2</edition>
            <isbn>978-3-96022-011-4</isbn>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref-hayles_how_2012-nb-article">
          <element-citation publication-type="book">
            <person-group person-group-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Hayles</surname>
                <given-names>N. Katherine</given-names>
              </name>
            </person-group>
            <source>How we think: Digital media and contemporary technogenesis</source>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Chicago ; London</publisher-loc>
            <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
            <isbn>978-0-226-32140-0 978-0-226-32142-4</isbn>
          </element-citation>
        </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <fn-group>
        <fn id="fn1-nb-article">
          <label>1</label>
          <p>Succession ist das ganze Wesen der Zeit.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn id="fn2-nb-article">
          <label>2</label>
          <p>In fact, Bergson distinguishes ‘la succession
    pure’ from ‘la succession se développant en espace’; he identifies
    Kantian succession as the second kind
    (<xref alt="1984, 151" rid="ref-bergson_oeuvres_1984-nb-article" ref-type="bibr">1984,
    151</xref>).</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </back>
  </sub-article>
</article>
